Sam Alman went on video this week to
tell the world that he was wrong about
the impact of advancing AI.
>> We've all been too ambitious on [music]
timelines even with this incredible
technology.
>> He now believes it will be something
slower, more like a rising tide.
Superficial layer. I agree. Going one
layer down though.
>> So first there was Open Claw then there
was Hermes and now there's Grockbot.
[music]
It's the most genuinely useful consumer
AI product that I've [music] seen this
year. Uh so I implemented Grockbot. I'm
going to be curious if any of you have
yet.
>> Uh yeah, I have. I've got um [music] 18
Grockpots working in a little swarm.
>> This week, uh Whimo announced a
significant redesign and cost savings.
Whimo unveiled the Ohigh vehicle, a
purposebuilt robo taxi minivan designed
by Chinese EV maker Zeer. News flash,
Google, Whimo, Alphabet, uh are
switching over to using and OEMing
Chinese hardware in order to achieve
Whimo objectives. I [music] would rather
see the West use a western hardware
stack rather than just white labeling
Chinese hardware. We're starting to see
honest to goodness vertical integration
here. And
>> now that's a moonshot. Ladies and
gentlemen,
>> welcome to Moonshots everyone. Your
number one podcast on all things AI and
exponential tech. Your favorite podcast
covering the most impactful news that is
changing your world. This is your front
row seat to the accelerating
singularity. I'm here once again with my
magnificent moonshot quintet, AWG, Dave
Blondon, Seem Ismael, Immad Mustach, and
I've got to pause and ask of course,
where is Waldo? See, where are you
today?
>> Um, I'm at Gulos uh airport in Sa Paulo
about to fly back. I did a talk today
for Ed McKenzie's forum to a couple
hundred of their CEOs. And and do they
feel excited or do they feel like
they're at death store?
>> Pretty much freaked out is the general
mood of the day.
>> Dude, I hate to break it to you, but
it's dead middle of winter. You're
missing summertime in the northern
hemisphere.
[laughter]
>> And Immod, how about yourself? Where are
you, pal?
>> I'm in Copenhagen today.
>> Copenhagen.
>> Yeah. About Tech Barbecue, the biggest
tech conference in the Scandies. It's
fantastic here. Although, you know, you
can't really say the institutions aren't
working because in Denmark they are.
>> So, it's wonderful covered.
>> And uh Alex and Dave, you're in your
normal haunts and I am too here in
Moonshots podcast headquarters. I can't
wait to greet you guys here in person.
See, you've been here.
>> But, uh Dave, yeah,
>> I'm currently bathed in this wonderful
fluorescent light that you can see
special effects for the singularity.
>> Well, you look beautiful nonetheless,
Peter. I thought that was your personal
man cave. Are we actually allowed into
that room?
>> Of course. [laughter]
>> Turn the camera around. I want to see
what it It's probably a junkyard on the
other side. That's [laughter]
>> a virtual background for everybody.
>> I bet it's got all your IV bags of all
of your [laughter]
>> Yeah, nobody naturally looks that good.
You're you're you're doing something.
>> And I'm Peter, your host and abundance
advocate. That's what I'm going to be
today. an advocate for optimism and
abundance as always.
>> What's I have a crazy confession to
make. Two days ago, I dragged Milan to
another rush concert.
[laughter]
>> In fact, we drove down we drove down to
Philadelphia cuz the last of the last
great, you know, The Who, the Rolling
Stones, Led Zeppelin. So, I I thought he
had to see it. So, selfishly, I took
him, dragged him along, and he was like,
"You're killing me, Dana." All these
geriatrics on with a with rush t-shirts
everywhere. But it was
event. It was my
>> You're a groupy. How does it feel to be
a groupy?
>> It's weird.
>> Well, everybody, let's get back here.
I'm Peter, your abundance advocate. Uh,
and as always, our mission here is to
help you understand what just happened,
what it means for you, and most
importantly, keep you optimistic about
the future. If you're new to Moonshots,
welcome. If you're a regular fellow
Moonshot, welcome back. Uh, got to give
love to our community. You know, we read
your comments and the outpouring is
amazing. I just going to read a few of
the comments from the last pod here.
Brian Anderson said, "The best AI
podcast on the internet. Just fabulous.
You guys are great." Uh Elvis Cotenna
said, "You guys are essentially
chronicling the singularity. What a
fabulous resource for the future." Brian
Clark said, "Moonshots is the best
content on YouTube, especially during
the singularity." Thank you for all you
guys do. and uh Brian and everybody, we
greatly appreciate you. The best way you
can thank us is take a moment if you
haven't already and hit the subscribe
button. You know, our moonshot on the
Moonshots podcast is to 100x our growth
and get to 10 million subscribers. So,
tell your friends, help share what we
are talking about, what's going on
during the singularity. You know, the
best antidote for fear is knowledge and
understanding, and that's what we try
and deliver. Uh also, you can now follow
us on X. Uh, our handle on X is
moonshots_pod.
Uh, and we put the clips and our podcast
on X. And really importantly, we want to
meet all of you guys. So, we're going to
be doing an AMA with everybody who
registers. We're going to do an AMA on
Zoom. Come meet us all. Ask us your
questions directly. If you want to
register for the AMA, go to
moonshots.com
and uh and we'll give you we'll be
letting you know. It's in about three
weeks we'll be doing this. So, register
for that and you'll have a chance to uh
plug in with us directly, get your
questions answered, want to know who you
are, what you're thinking about, really
connect with all of you to help you on
this incredible journey. Okay, so let's
buckle up. Another amazing week during
the Singularity. As always, AI is
getting faster, cheaper, and smarter.
Today, we're going to cover about a
dozen stories that have been breaking.
Uh let's begin. A quick summary. Google
is back with Gemini crushing agent
benchmarks. Nvidia is fighting against
the Chinese model domination with its
own ope models. AI is playing Cupid,
connecting college kids on dates. Whimo
has just released the sixth generation
vehicle. Elon is projecting 10,000
Starship flights per year. And Americans
are even more emphatic about saying,
"Please do not build a data center in
our backyard." So, uh, life on the
cutting edge is accelerating. Again,
thank you for joining us. Uh guys, I
don't know about you, but uh keeping up
with all the stories. Uh Alex, thank you
for everything you submit. Immod See,
you know, uh just parsing through them.
And you need to know we parse through
probably 400 stories to narrow it down
to 15 or so. And we're podcasting twice
a week. Uh and it's, you know, the speed
is blinding. Uh well I I think that
comment on chronicling the singularity
too is very poignant from one of one of
the fans there. You know Alex's
innermost loop uh daily feed is is
trying to do exactly that every every
relevant event. But there's a tendency
to say well look exponential change is
going to be with us forever. Are we
really chronicling a moment in time? But
the reality is we're in this step
function. You know society pre-s
singularity and society post singularity
are step function different. And this
moment of transition actually is worth
capturing every single event. So I
really do think that the storyline that
we're capturing here will last for
millennia.
>> It's, you know, do you remember how slow
it was? [laughter]
>> My my life is so different than two
years ago. Like just minuteby minute. I
can't even tell you how different it is.
And a lot of people haven't made that
leap yet, but they will. You know,
everyone will see it a year from today.
We'll all be like, "Wow, remember how
slow it was?" Yeah, I think we're like
the first responders to the singularity.
[laughter]
>> I like that. This episode is sponsored
by Google for startups. Think about this
for a second. You now have access to the
same generative AI models that cost
hundreds of millions of dollars to
train. Google's startup technical
[music] guide for generative media gives
you a complete blueprint for deploying
Google DeepMind's models in production.
Images, video, audio, all of it. Real
architecture, real results. Find the
link in the show notes below.
Our first article is an interesting one
here. Uh let me jump into it because uh
it's one that tells us that as fast as
the technology is, it's hitting the
reality of society and humans. So Sam
Alman went on video this week to tell
the world that he was wrong about the
impact of advancing AI, that the impact
is actually slower than he originally
expected. And while Sam, you know, used
to believe society would be, you know,
experience a dramatic disruption on the
arrival of AGI, he now believes it will
be something slower, more like a rising
tide. Uh Sam says factors like the
economic inertia, institutional lag, the
inability of humans to rapidly adapt to
change are combining to slow the curve.
Ultimately, the singularity, like you
just said, Dave, is a process um and not
just a singular event. Let me share the
video here and take a moment to see what
uh what Sam actually had to say. And I
thought when we got to GBT4, which was
back in 20 23, I think, uh, that very
quickly after that, there was going to
be much more disruption in software
business being up for grabs right right
away than it turned out to be. And the
thing that I think I was wrong about a
few things. Uh, but one of them in terms
of the speed, one of them is the economy
just has so much inertia. People keep
doing the same things they're doing.
They keep buying from the same uh, you
know, company. They keep sort of wanting
to use their tools in the same way. I
think this is actually a positive in
many ways and it's going to make this
big transition in front of us go
smoother and slower. I'm grateful for
it. But I think it means we've all been
too ambitious on timelines even with
this incredible technology. I think AI
is one of the most incredible
technologies humanity has ever invented.
Society and the economy will adapt more
slowly.
>> See, we've talked about the inertia of
humans so much. What do you think about
this?
So this is the bottleneck of technology
being hit with the bottleneck of
coordination, incentives, regulatory and
so on. Right? This is the uh in
extraordinary difficulty where
technology is moving exponentially and
our organizations and our institutions
are linear and frontier labs made the
mistake of confusing technical
possibility with institutional
deployment and that those are two very
very different layer. You know Steuart
Brand had that concept of pace layers
where technology moves at one layer like
an ocean current at the top. That's very
kind of swift, but way down in the
ocean, uh, regulatory government changes
very slow slowly. This has good effects
and bad effects. In our world, it's bad
because it's slowing down the
implementation of some of these things.
God help me. It just took me 2 hours to
get to the airport just now. And
passenger drones, which have been ready
for a decade technologically, but we're
waiting for infrastructure. We're
waiting for regulatory to catch up,
could have done it in 10 minutes. And
so,
>> S Paulo needs a bed for sure.
>> We we lots of places need a bed. This is
one of the worst and I think the big
work now is how do we accelerate
institutional acceleration and
institutional development as the word I
think Alex uses is co-scaling right we
have to scale our organizations and our
institutions to keep pace with the
technology because it's not storing down
and that gap is where all the stress is
coming from so for me the singularity is
not when machine become becomes
infinitely capable it's when institution
can't adapt at all to that rate of
capability of you and that is what we
that was the breaking point. We're kind
of there now.
>> Alex, you sent me the story. What are
your thoughts about Sam's comments?
>> Yeah, a few different layers. Uh so at
at the superficial layer, I obviously
agree with Sam's comments more broadly.
I've made the point on this pod and
otherwise that singularity as a step
function is just totally nonsensical.
It's an interval in time that we're in
the middle of. So superficial layer, I
agree. Going one layer down though, I I
don't think I agree with necessarily the
premise that societal inertia is the
villain for slowing down or spreading
out the singularity sigmoid. I think the
villain if there is one in this story is
actually abstraction layers. I I think
it's if you if you say you develop like
a new engine for a car, you develop an
electric engine versus the internal
combustion engine, there's a very
natural layering of the stack whereby
people still want to drive cars. So they
drive an electric car, but under the
hood it's completely unrecognizable. So
one abstraction layer down, there's
total step function in the technology,
but you go up a layer, it's still a car
with a recognizable steering wheel,
recognizable wheels, and so on. So I
think the enemy of honest to goodness
radical transformative progress of the
type that I think Sam is gesturing at is
actually the existence and inertia of
the abstraction stack of the economy not
the economy more broadly which is
prescriptive. If if you believe that
theory of the case then if you want
faster progress that Sam is I I can't
quite tell either bemoning the lack of
fast progress while also paying homage
to the lack of fast progress.
I think he feels relieved by this.
>> He has a way of sometimes like saying
two things at once. Uh so I think he's
sort of expressing gratitude for the
slowness while also bemoning it. Uh so
but if you want to go faster, this
theory of the case is prescriptive. It
if you want to go faster, pull in Elon
and vertically integrate to erase the
barriers between abstraction layers. You
do that and things can go much more
quickly. If Sam or OpenAI want to move
much more quickly, they should be much
more vertically integrated so that they
can move layers. Presumably, he's
gesturing at layers above the OpenAI
model layer in the stack. Own or at
least vertically integrate more of that
or go down a layer with Stargate. Open
AAI has pretty publicly abandoned its
original Stargate strategy of owning
their own data centers. Now they're just
leasing. if they want to see more
transformative progress, go down a few
layers and vertically integrate like
with the jalapeno chips own as much of
the stack vertically integrated as they
can. They can move really quickly and I
think we're seeing a lot of the uh the
labs beginning to vertically integrate.
I mean everybody we'll talk about a
story here where Nvidia is beginning to
vertically integrate. Uh Emod, do you
agree with Sam?
>> Yeah, I think a couple of points on
this. Um, first, you know, I agree with
Alex and kind of artificial intelligence
meeting institutional stupidity and
stupidity tax as Elon calls it still
being very high on these interface and
abstraction points. But I think it's
interesting cuz we just had a time
article come out. I haven't read it uh
where they went in depth with OpenAI and
Sam saying we'll have AGI by the end of
this year
>> for a timeline. And on the other side,
he's saying well you know I've been
surprised by diffusion. Here's the
reality. The models weren't good enough
until a few months ago. The code they
were writing was garbage a year ago,
relatively speaking. Then it was okay.
Now you don't look at the code anymore.
You think about math. 03 was the first
model a year or so ago that I could use.
Small GPT 5.6 Soul is the first really
good math model. And so the application
of intelligence to high leverage and
diffusion of it, it's being wrapped in
instinct type rappers. It's iMessage.
It's this chat backed by actually
competent intelligence which has
literally only been around now for maybe
a month or two. So I think it's not
surprising because I wouldn't use GPT4.
Can you imagine using GPT4 in a
codebase? you know remembering that
[laughter]
>> or you mean for any institutional
process like it's a good thing there
wasn't a diffusion of innovation there
because otherwise companies would fall
apart
>> and like you know as Alex said some says
two things at once I think open AI is
trying to find its narrative right now
you know on the one hand agi is here on
the other hand oh you know it doesn't
really move that fast we're all good
don't worry about us and this is hacking
that but that's not that big deal
they're just trying to find where that
narrative sticks I think [clears throat]
>> Dave your thoughts question, please.
>> Well, I'll give you a completely
different twist on this because, you
know, I interviewed Sam, you know, back
when his he was innocent and star
stareyed before the singularity kicked
off and then his house got firebombed,
you know, with a baby inside. Uh, and
now there's a different Sam. Same is
true with Dario. Same is true like
you're only going to hear straight balls
and strikes here on this podcast. And I
don't even know how long that will last,
but as of right now, we're just telling
you as it is. But Sam woke up and said,
"Well, my god, I I literally can't get
into the office cuz the pickers are
lined up." Remember when we were there,
Peter? Like, you have to fight through
the pickers to get to the door. And now
it's all armed security. So, what
happened in the interim is they woke up
and realized society can't flip on a
dime. And and all this disruption that
you're talking about, all these
capabilities you're talking about are
scaring many more people than are
rallying to your cause. And that's why
so many states are anti-data center
right now. And is that good for open AI?
God, no.
>> So now they're going to start picking
and choosing their words a lot more
carefully and they're going to actually
have a PR strategy. So you know, if you
want to know what's actually happening,
you can still tune in here, but you
can't listen directly to Sam Daario
anymore. Elon always says exactly what
he's saying.
>> They're preipo, so they're going to say
what it takes to calm the masses out
there to some degree.
>> You know, there's the way I describe it,
uh, Alexad is an impedance mismatch,
right? We have these incredibly powerful
tools that are becoming more powerful by
the moment and when they run into an
institution, governments in particular,
which are typically linear or sublinear
or a company or an individual who can't
take advantage of it, you have one of
two options. You turn it over fully the
AI and you give it an objective
function. you say make me maximally
profitable or make me look maximally
intelligent or run my government more
sufficiently or you try and um and get
in the middle and we're going to talk
about a little bit later a article from
the Wall Street Journal where AI is
exhausting us all. Uh and if the human
is in that that uh interface loop at
that you know impedance mismatch point
um it breaks very quickly. I was going
to make some stupid joke about uh
reflections happening at impedance
mismatches. But I I I I think more
seriously there are all sorts of
metaphors that one can reach for.
Impedance mismatch maybe on the circuit
side is one. But the supply and demand
as well. Open AI and anthropic largely
have an over supply of intelligence or
super intelligence. And at least one of
the things that I've learned from the
past few months of participating in the
market and watching the market is not
all of the market has the demand for the
super intelligence that they're
supplying or is is ready to have the
demand or knows how to use the demand if
the supply is available. So another
metaphor is just markets and clearing.
And right now the clearing of supply
meeting demand, the the two curves from
economics 101 crossing each other aren't
necessarily crossing for all cases at a
favorable point. And that's I I think
maybe through a more economicsy lens
what Sam may be gesturing at.
>> Well, just to put sci-fi lens on this
too, I think that there there was a
moment in time a year ago where the
greatest AI ambition was to take your
job. and you know, wow, that'll unleash
a lot of value and profit in the
economy. It transitioned beyond that in
a heartbeat to I don't even care about
your job. I have deeper thoughts that
I'm working on. And and so we're in that
new era where the AI is starting to
think, well, if I discover new physics,
new medicine that never existed in the
world, I can add a lot more valuable
than taking away your job. And so it
just leapt from prehistoric to future AI
in the last month, in the last couple of
releases.
>> I think it's a fascinating point, Dave.
Maybe I'd generalize further on the
sci-fi front. There are so many, I
think, inane sci-fi movie plots with
grabby aliens that are coming and
invading Earth because they want our
resources. They're not going to want our
resources, our resources. If if you're
super intelligent civilization, you
don't need human slave labor or Earth's
valuable metals or whatever, you're
going to long ago. Yeah, they need our
water. Come on. So like seriously with
with transcendent super intelligence I I
completely agree with the sentiment that
replacing human labor lasts for about 5
minutes and then you move beyond that.
>> Yeah.
>> And the guy it's really interesting to
watch the guys you know Sam also has
moved on beyond that in a heartbeat. You
know a couple of events and a couple new
models and now he's like oh my god why
why do I even care about automating a
banker or automating an insurance agent?
this that mattered to me last year for a
few minutes and I just literally don't
care anymore.
>> But I I do think Dave, I do think that
these these uh frontier labs and I I
really hate calling them labs because
they're they're frontier companies if
you would um are going to reach up the
stack. they're going to build fully
verticalized finance companies,
insurance companies, you know,
consulting companies and so forth on top
of theirs or they'll partner to do that
and and that will uh you know,
accelerate all of these areas.
>> Even if I think about insurance though,
just as a C because I'm, you know, I'm
the chairman of a very large insurance
company, public company, and uh they
move, they cared about like auto
insurance a year ago. Now they're like,
"Well, wait, all these new things, all
these data centers, all these robots,
the the new insurance categories that AI
is generating are bigger than the legacy
insurance industry." Yeah.
>> So, so it's just moved from replace the
old to who cares about the old. Let's
just start thinking about an entirely
new economy, a new world, a new AI, and
we'll just live within ourselves. You
know, we don't need to disrupt everybody
who's going to get angry and vote
against us. Let's go ahead and just live
within ourselves.
>> I think that is the 30 Peter. I think
that is the $30 trillion question,
though. If you're a Frontier Lab, one of
two, call them American Frontier Labs,
maybe four, depending on how you count.
Is it more natural in an era when maybe
you're facing margin pressure on your
model releases to go upstack or
downstack? I think it's actually more
ergonomic for them to go downstack and
design their own chips and compete with
Nvidia and design and operate their data
centers and energy.
>> I think they're going to do it all. And
Alex, you you called out a number there
I was about to reference as well. We
just saw, you know, Daario or or
Anthropic state that their total
addressable market is $30 trillion.
>> I wonder where that number came from.
Surely it's it's pure coincidence that
the GDP of America is 30 trillion.
>> Yep. [laughter]
>> I'm going to move us on our next story.
Uh let's talk about Grockbot. So, first
it was OpenClaw, then there was Hermes,
and now there's Grockbot from Space XAI.
So, Grockbot launched on August 11th uh
in an early beta. It's Elon's entry into
the agentic AI space, and it's the most
genuinely useful consumer AI product
that I've seen this year. Uh so, I
implemented Grockbot. I'm going to be
curious if any of you have yet. And so,
each bot gets its own dedicated cloud
computer with a browser, a terminal, and
the ability to log into your actual
apps. You message Grockbot like you'd
message a colleague, not a chatbot. um a
chief of staff, you know, sits on top
and it's which case for me it's Skippy
with specialists on sales, operations,
research, engineering, you know, any sub
agents you want. And these multiple bots
run in parallel. They message each other
and only pull you in on judgment calls.
So, there's a huge amount of excitement
on Grockbot. It's been flooding the
internet. Uh has anybody here played
with it yet?
>> I've been playing quite extensively with
it. Um
>> Okay. What do you Uh I I I love it. I
think the interface and the ease of use
is fast is amazing. You're losing a lot
of kind of customizability under the
hood, but it's a powerful thing. Do you
know you're you're making a transition
from asking an AI to assigning work
>> and so persistent autonomous agent is
like it's like a new form of labor.
>> And so now you have this completely new
category. You know, Peter, we have that
staff on demand attribute in EXO, right?
This is that taken to its logical
extreme where staff are staff recruiting
time and coordination cost has gone to
like pretty much zero. So the the when
I'm looking at it from my book
perspective, the optimal organizational
structure completely changes. Humans set
objectives and leave everything else to
the AI.
>> Amazing. Uh Immod, have you played with
it?
>> Uh yeah, I have. I've got um 18
Grockbots working in a little swarm and
I've given them control via tail scale
of a MacBook M4 Max, a 5090 and a range
of other computers as well, plus all my
subscriptions. So, I'm really testing it
out. One of the fun ones that I've got
is I have a Grock Bot called Attellier
that has a little team of artists and
it's trying to learn art and it's not
doing very well or it's doing very well.
I don't know. I'm not a aesthetic enough
to do it. [laughter] Uh, every day it
goes through its pieces and it comes up
with its main one and I just shared one
of them on the um chat which is vinyl
with a piece of hair on it. I was like
where is that from? [laughter] Where's
it getting its aesthetic kind of
responsibilities? So if you look at the
chat I just shared that
>> and when it comes up with the when it
comes up with a banana with a piece of
tape then you'll get worried.
>> Well it was like this is my inner space
and it was showing all these wonderful
things and now it's getting like kind of
weird but maybe I just don't understand
art. I don't know. Um, but it is
genuinely useful and I think one of the
more powerful things, like I said, is
you can actually cuz it's got a computer
inside, you can give it another shell
because the computer's decent, but you
can actually have it take over an entire
MacBook M4 or something like that. So,
I've got subbots that have other
capabilities. So, right now it's
installing like the new um GLM model and
another one's installing and testing
Alibaba model. One of them was
optimizing um the Alibaba 27B model to
run faster on a 5090. So added 76% to
performance at 64K context.
>> Love it. You know, I do think this is
going to be uh an important revenue
engine for for XAI. Uh I think we're
going to start to see their revenue
numbers creep up as they as they get
this. I mean, I stepped up a few hundred
bucks on my uh my payments uh to Elon.
So I think others Dave, you haven't
played yet, have you?
Uh, well, I just signed off on 100K of
Swarm agents. We're running our 5,000
Kimmies again today, which is why I'm
wearing my my Swarm it shirt here. But
this is the theme of the month. I think
that all of our ai interactions to date
have been very much one-on-one.
And now the agents are so abundant that
you want to try and use a workforce of
six and then 50 and then a thousand. And
I think within 3 months you'd be talking
about, you know, 50,000 agents that can
in parallel work for you. But it's very
similar to trying to manage an
organization. You're like, well, what's
everyone doing? I don't know. It's
getting really confusing. Are are people
being productive? I can't tell. And so,
you really have to start thinking hard
about your org structure and your
reporting structure to know if your
agents are doing anything useful. And so
I I really want our team here to get
ahead of that and and start, you know,
go ahead and burn the money but learn
quickly and then we'll get get a handle
on
>> this is what I mean by the
organizational singularity because the
company starts to look less than less
like an org chart and more like a
continuously orchestrated intelligence
network and that is such a big shift.
It's like ridiculously big compared to
everything we've ever done.
>> Yeah.
>> I'll give you a hot take.
Sorry. Go ahead, Alex.
>> I I don't take Alex. Hot take. People
love the hot takes. Um I I I don't think
this is actually the interface of the
future. So what's perhaps most
interesting about Grockbot is it
presents like a a messaging app like
WhatsApp or iMessage where you have a
pane of the the various agents that are
in your fleet and you can have
conversations with them and they can
message each other and there's a
computer use assistant angle. But I
don't think that's how it scales. That's
completely unscalable. If if agent-based
scaling, if scaling the size of your
fleet becomes one of the most essential
scaling laws like inference time scaling
has ended up being in the era of
reasoning based models, we're not going
to want to ask individuals or even
enterprises to manage millions of
agents. That that's completely
unergonomic. We're going to want agents
managing other agents. In which case the
exercise of trying to graft a human
organization or like the Slack or
chatbased interface for humans managing
other humans is not going to extend. We
we'll look at this like vaudeville the
vaudeville era of agents and say this
was a naive attempt to graft human
organizational structures onto humans
managing agents. The only better manager
for agents is other agents and this
doesn't seem to fully internalize that
lesson. Selene, what do you think about
Alex's comment?
>> Um, I think it's a I agree with Alex on
the interface comment. This is it like
an UI that's temporary. I love the way
he says it presents like as if it
presents like an illness. It presents
like a a messaging app and I think
that's a temporary one while we figure
out new interfaces. But for now, that's
a very workable one for coordinating a
bunch of agents. We'll come up with all
sorts of others. I think we'll go rotate
through a whole set of these, but I
think the his core comments are as usual
with Alex are absolutely dead on.
>> Yeah, it's maybe it's an illness for for
which the medication that I prescribe is
a good dosage of the the bitter lesson
pill.
>> Yeah. I also think this is what humans
are ready to play with,
>> right? I think I think that, you know,
again, it's moving people along the
process. if you provided
something that was you know completely
different uh I think there would be less
adoption and so
>> that's that's the the abstraction layer
stack and Sam saying why are things so
slow and the answer is people who are
one or two layers up from you in the
stack expect the old things so you have
to abstract yourself in a familiar
interface
>> well it's also Peter it goes back to
remember the comments we made about
exponential technology become hits the
vertical and goes up the near occur when
it becomes usable. And what Elon's done
with this layer is made AI agents usable
to a big set of people. It'll change
again as people become more used to it
and they see what how the hell is
operating. The architecture may not be
great, etc. But for now, this is a
powerful entry point.
>> Yeah, I I agree. I just, you know, kudos
to Elon and the Cursor team for making
this happen. Uh, by the way, I invited
Alex Finn to come back to the Abundance
Summit in March, uh, since he's been
doing a lot of amazing, you know,
Grockbot videos. If you haven't seen his
Grockbot videos yet, go and check them
out. He'll teach you how to use it and
what's special about it. And I said,
Alex, if if Grockbot is still the
hottest thing in March of 2027 at the
Abundance Summit, teach that. If it's
not, teach whatever is the latest
hottest thing. But it's, you know, I
think people need to be using these
agentic systems. Um, I'm still using
Hermes and Grockbot and um, hey, we'll
see. Let's move on to our next
conversation, uh, which is Google is
back. So, Google's Gemini 3.7 Flash just
took the top spot on AI AA analyst agent
benchmark, the gold standard for
measuring how well AI models handle
complex real world data analysis tasks.
Across 80 tasks in 14 business and
scientific domains, Gemini 3.7 Flash
delivered the highest overall accuracy
while completing tasks up to 90% faster
and then took top models 2.4 times
faster than the GPT 5.6 Terra. So on the
AA uh analyst agent benchmark which
we're showing on the slide here uh
Gemini 3.7 flash achieved a 60% pass
rate beating Claude Opus 5 at 54% and
Fable 5 at 49%. So, Alex, um, you know,
many times, you know, you've said,
others have said, you know, Gemini is
dead. Uh, let's read the epitap,
counting them out of the frontier model
race. They've now shipped the fastest,
most accurate agent model in the world.
And by the way, we've seen this over and
over again, right? We saw Meta was dead.
What the heck is Meta doing? And then it
comes out with its models. XAI is is is
out of the race and they come back. So,
to me, it seems like uh none of these
players are out of the race. They're
maybe in stealth mode. They're holding
back, but they're coming back with a
with a fast, furious uh punch to try and
take the top position. What do you make
of this, Alex?
>> Do you want me to reassure you that
Google still has a chance, or do you
want me to to give you the the facts
unvarnished?
>> Yeah, you got there pretty hard. Defend
yourself, Alex.
>> Okay, so I I'll give you the unvarnished
case here. Uh Google's still out of the
running for the capability frontier. I
was looking at this expect that okay
>> scratching my head like Gemini 3.7 flash
is nowhere near the the top of the
capability frontier. So why is it doing
so well on this one benchmark uh
artificial analysis analyst agent? So
you have to look at the benchmark
itself. So the benchmark itself this is
a benchmark for agents ability to
perform quantis on real world
spreadsheets and docs. But wait for it,
its metric for success is the share of
questions answered correctly on all five
attempts. So th this is a benchmark that
is fine-tuned for reliability. It
rewards agents that give the same
answer, basically the same answer every
time and obviously want it to be the
right answer, but it penalizes
stochasticity. It penalizes in some
sense creativity. Maybe we don't want
creativity out of our analysts. I don't
know. But it it it promotes reliability
uh and determinism. Uh interestingly,
there's no time constraint. I had to
check that as well to see. But I I think
you can see in this uh where Google fell
off the capability frontier. At least I
So I'll give you my conspiracy theory
for what this one outperformance on this
one benchmark suggests. I think that
maybe what's been going on this
obviously there are a few other factors
but I think Google uh Google deep mind
has been under material pressure to
optimize their models for two things
largely owing to Google search. So if if
we rewind the the video to several
months ago or a year ago, people were
hand ringing, oh, isn't Google, aren't
the 10 blue links going to face an
existential threat from all of these
frontier models and chat bots and
reasoning agents that can just replace
the need to Google at all? And Google's
response was uh to self-disrupt by
building the Gemini series or at least
some flash variants thereof directly
into the one boxes. But people expect
Google search results to be very fast,
low latency, and they expect them to be
very reliable, not returning wildly
different or unpredictable answers each
time. And I think those two pressures
from the desire to embed Gemini inside
Google search have optimized through
competitive internal pressures for
probably scarce compute. The Gemini
models, especially like Flash, note that
there's no Gemini 3.7 Pro anywhere. It's
just Flash. It's small, it's fast, and
it's reliable. I think this is
overoptimized for clock speed, like wall
clock speed and determinism. And as a
result, it does well on the one
benchmark that rewards highly reliable
answers and underperforms. Yeah, it's
benchmaxing for basically spreadsheet
analysis to be highly reliable.
>> Emma, do you agree?
>> Um, yeah, I kind of agree with that a
little bit with Alex. Uh I think the
Gemini models the way they are used now
is for organizing data like you can
track any type of modality of data and
flash is a perfectly decent model but
[snorts] it's not as good as the Chinese
models especially the new GLM flash
that's just come out that's 10 times
cheaper for the same performance. Um
Google did do a preview of Gemini 3.5
Pro but it just couldn't keep up. This
is kind of a key thing and you can't
accuse them of not having enough compute
or it being a scarce resource. They
literally have millions of chips. I
think it's more been about turnover and
some institutional malaise coming in
that they can't push through to this
frontier level cuz Google has all the
data in the world. It has the links of
what people search for. It has Gemini as
a captive thing. But you know, has the
Gemini app advanced at all? Not really.
The only real place I think you've seen
innovation on the AI side is somewhat
the kind of AI studio stuff is decent
and the notebook LM stuff is continuing
to be fantastic. But aside from that,
again, they've been falling behind in
everything except for omnimodal
um and video. They're still actually
quite accurate. But even then, the
Chinese are coming for their lunch. Like
why not just post train on Chinese
models at this point if you're Google?
>> It may come to that. I I think people
don't realize how compute starved Google
is though internally. I mean, this has
been widely reported. You think Google
has all of the the compute, the the
CPUs, the TPUs, and the GPUs in the
world. It's been widely reported at this
point. They they have internal regular
meetings to try to aortion out their
scarce compute. And that the three main
constituencies in inside Google that are
fighting for for the flops are one,
Google Cloud Platform, which is
basically fighting on behalf of external
users. Two, Google DeepMind that's
fighting for training and inference
flops. And then three, Google search uh
at which is needs its own flops
especially as search becomes more
intelligent. So so my again my theory of
the case here is there actually is
resource starvation inside Google and as
a result
>> we talked about this over and over again
every company is comput starved at this
point. There is no company that's got
enough compute. So what makes I mean
Google's got more compute than anybody
at this point. They're just distributing
it across all of their products and
services. Critically, Google has other
consumers fighting for their own compute
internally besides AI. Whereas, if
you're open AI or anthropic, no, you
don't have any other nonAI users
fighting for it.
>> Mhm.
>> Fair enough.
>> Google's landing like 3 million TPUs
this year. Like I think there's relative
levels of compute constraint like we've
got a 100,000 chips versus a million
chips versus 10,000 to train a frontier
level or close to frontier level let's
say better than Gemini model today needs
2 to 4,000 TPUs and the evidence of that
is the Chinese did it and they open
sourced them and we know exactly how
they're built given Google's data that
goes into Gemini Flash applying exactly
the same architecture as GLM or Kimmy,
you should have a better outcome. But
they're not doing that for some reason.
And that doesn't require 10,000 100,000
chips. It requires
>> That's a really important point about
it's like it's Yeah. 2 to 4,000 GPUs for
60 to 90 days.
>> That is a microscopic investment by
Google standards. So it's exactly right.
It has nothing to do with compute
dominance and everything to do with
talent attrition. It's a great point.
>> No, but this is institutional failure,
isn't it? Because again, you know how to
build a Kimmy model. you know how to
build a GLM model and so if Google take
the data that they put into Gemini and
copied the exact model architecture you
should have a better model on the other
side and if you don't you have to ask
real questions why well and then then
think about it from the person's career
point of view like the ego blow like you
would have to be I'm the most wellunded
top AI engineer in the world and the
Chinese just kicked my ass to go tell my
boss you know what I give up let's go
download Kimmy do the rational thing and
then tune it, you know, you can't say
that because you you look like an idiot
and that's where they are. You know,
people are leaving in droves to try and
get a clean start and a fresh sheet of
paper and but yeah, you just got
bypassed with massive advantages and
resources.
>> So guys, you can't admit it
>> in the US closed labs, right, between
OpenAI, Anthropic um and uh and Google
and XAI. Who's in the best position
here? I mean who's got
>> now or two years in the future
>> now? Questionic.
Yeah, right now anthropic has the
strongest forgetting about price or
perform or you know time wall clock
anthropic has the strongest model that's
generally available fable 5 there are
hordes
>> not I'm not speaking about model in
terms of positioned with compute and the
speed at which they're deploying models
and their ability to you know uh to I
guess continue their their dominance.
Um,
>> well, here's the thing, Peter. There's
no easy answer because Anthropic is in
the best position by far and hordes of
very talented people are going there
purely because they want to see the
singularity emerge. Like, it's it's like
the birth of the phoenix. I want to be
there on that day,
>> but they're totally reliant on Elon for
the compute. Elon can rip the soul out
of anthropic any day. And he's got the
cursor guys now. He spent $60 billion
getting them. They're brilliant and
they're starting to roll out cool stuff
and they're starting to do the training.
So, yeah. you know, if you said two
years in the future, then it's really
tricky because Anthropic and Elon are
like, I don't know. It's it's a really
interesting risk.
>> I just want to give our listeners an
understanding of sort of the, you know,
sort of the terrain out there. Uh, we've
got, you know, the the US labs competing
against each other and the Chinese labs
continually pummeling them. We're going
to talk about that in a moment. So, uh,
yeah, I mean, anthropics the most
advanced, but their compute, uh, they
don't own their compute, which is a
problem.
>> I would disagree with anthropic being
the most advanced.
Who do you believe?
>> Open AAI. Open AAI aside from the
Chinese labs owned the Pareto Frontier.
From Luna now being free to everyone to
again as a mathematician GPT 5.6 Pro is
the only quality math model. I have no
idea what magic they're doing with Fable
to actually get math results because it
makes so many mistakes.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Totally right.
>> GPT 5.6 Pro is the only proper frontier
model.
>> Totally right. Yeah. We switched over to
Soul actually. Everybody over here is
like, "God, this fable has lost its
mind." But but you know, the the
argument there is that, well, inside
Anthropic, they have Mythos 2 now. So,
they're another level ahead and they
won't release it to us. Oh, maybe. We
can't tell. But for our use case, you
know, on hard problems, hard engineering
and hard math, yeah, we switched
everything over to soul. So totally
agree am
>> even if it was Methos 2 again you would
see them releasing lowhanging
breakthroughs which the OpenAI have done
with Astra and OpenAI again have lined
up the compute they have more capital
raised than Anthropic they had the 120
billion round so they can burn a few
years of market capture they have the
consumer now moving to enterprise with
enterprise shifting and I think
Anthropic for all of their talent and
their access to GPUs actually Google
just built them a gigantic TPU like
million in deployment. Um, they're
shooting themselves in the foot from an
institutional perspective because Opus 5
is unpleasant. Fable is unpleasant to
use. And I don't think it's going to get
more pleasant to use.
>> Yeah. Didn't Alex say he he actively
hates Opus 5?
>> I said I said that.
>> I I did say I I don't like Opus 5. I I
prefer Fable 5, but I I think the the
truth on the frontier is materially more
nuanced. Like again if you look emot for
example at Frontier Math Tier 4 it it is
the case that Fable 5 outperforms
ironically OpenAI's latest solid model
even though OpenAI was the primary
sponsor behind Epic developing the
Frontier Math tier 4 model. So I I think
the the truth you know is a little bit
blurry in part because the Frontier
isn't zero dimensional. It's it's a
oneplus dimensional frontier where if
you're willing to pay a lot uh and wait
a long time for fable 5 to do something
it's impressive but if you're resource
starved cash starved time starved then
you can probably get better performance
at a different point on the optimal cost
frontier by say using salt. I just want
to point out to everybody listening,
it's not it's not obvious, right? There
there is uh a lot going on and then
we're seeing China constantly leap frog.
So, you
>> I have a I have a hot take. These
frontier labs are facing the innovators
dilemma from hell, right? We talked
about this before because you've got the
Chinese open source models from one
angle, compute constraints on another
angle, and you've got government
regulatory on a third angle. this is
like a nightmare while everybody else is
moving quickly with open source models.
So, this is a very difficult place to
be. And the good news is you can see um
that they're all trying to get into
certain verticals and get into revenue
streams as fast as possible to reduce
that dependence on the frontier model
and being the edge as their core
innovator's capability.
>> I mean the abundance take on this is we
as the consumers and the users are the
beneficiary. It's demonetizing very
rapidly at the same time that it's
expanding.
>> When Frontier Labs compete, you win.
>> Yes, we all win. All right, I'm going to
move us on. Uh we've been saying for
some time on this pod that the US needs
a powerful openweight model to contend
with what's coming out of China. And
this week, Nvidia is stepping up,
pouring $6 billion into developing an
open-source AI model and inference
infrastructure designed to give US
developers a domestic alternative
Alibaba, Deepseek, and Kimmy. The deal
struck between Nvidia and the AI startup
Poolside aims to build one of the
world's most powerful openweight models.
By building its own opin, Nvidia is
moving up the stack. We've discussed
this from silicon to software
positioning itself not just as a
chipmaker for AI but as a platform
provider for openweight uh ecosystems.
You know from my point of view it looks
like everybody's going up and down the
stack. Uh we've seen anthropic we've
seen open AAI obviously uh SpaceX AI uh
is doing the same. Immod let's go to you
first. What are your thoughts on Nvidia
and Poolside? Yeah. So, I've been
talking to some of the investors out
here like at this um tech barbecue
conference who invested in Poolside
originally. They tried to raise $2
billion at the end of last year.
>> So, who is Poolside? First of all,
>> uh Poolside is a company. I believe it
was the ex GitHub.
>> Yeah. The former CTO of GitHub,
>> former CTO, Issa Kant um and others.
They set up and they wanted to
originally create a coding model. Then
they moved to an open-source model and
model factory called Lagona that
outperformed uh Thinking Machine's
Inkling model when it first came out.
They tried at the turn of the no a few
months ago to raise $2 billion for a
massive Blackwell cluster and they
couldn't. So they lost that cluster and
they were like this is the table stakes
we need. But they built a really great
solid open-source model for its size.
And so now what they've done is they've
benefited from this weird Nvidia um aqua
hire type thing where Nvidia is like we
need to build great open- source models
to increase demand for our technology on
the Neatron stack. So the first thing
they did actually was they hired and I
don't think it's been announced yet
Ashish Viswani's team from Essential AI.
um he was one of the founders of the um
one of the authors on the attention is
all you need paper and now they're going
to be making more and more acquisitions
up and down the open source stack to be
the leader in open source because again
that drives demand for the GPUs more
than anything um so I think this is just
the first or well not the first this is
the main one but there'll be many more
acquisitions and they'll have a full
open-source stack uh this is the Neatron
coalition so a lot of the classic ones
like Mistral and Coher and others won't
be building open source models anymore.
They'll be building to the Nvidia
reference design.
>> Alex,
>> I think maybe I I I could say something
nice about the American open-source
community uh and openweight models
moving in a positive direction.
Obviously, Nvidia had invested I think
about a billion dollars in this company
previously and now through this I'd call
it a acquisition now they're they're
finally sort of uh turbocharging their
own Neotron community. more interesting
to me that acquisitions or concerning
perhaps that acquisitions still need to
happen in this day and age. It's also I
I think bizarre if if you follow some of
the recent acquisitions, the my original
take on this was this is just an an
attempt to avoid regulatory scrutiny or
antitrust scrutiny. But I've started to
see now some of the other acquisition
targets come back to life. the what I
had sort of left for dead as the carcass
of the original company where all of the
the founding team comes over and all of
the core IP was quote unquote
non-exclusively licensed which I think
my understanding was was the case here
as well where Nvidia is non-exclusively
licensing key poolside IP. I will be
watching closely what happens to the
part of poolside that did not come to
Nvidia. I I think my original
expectation that this is just a carcass
left over after the hunt that is being
left behind purely to avoid regulatory
scrutiny may actually have life to it
and not investment advice but could
actually be in some sense even more
interesting than the part that goes over
to Nvidia.
>> I mean there's a lot of pressure for the
US to develop top tier open-source
platforms right now. Uh Dave, what are
you what's your take?
>> Yeah, curious Alex, you said kind of
quickly there. surprised that
acquisitions need to exist in this day
and age. But I got calls from both Merur
and from Orin, our good buddy Kush
Bavaria, who was on the pod a week ago,
uh, looking for acquisition targets to
accelerate. You know, that the hiring
cycle is too slow. I need groups of
three, 10, 15 people that work really
well together. I don't care what it
costs. Like, send them to me tomorrow.
So, it seems to be, you know, at least
in terms of my inbound, like an all-time
high in acquisition. Why do you think it
should be a thing of the past?
Well, so I I would distinguish between
talent acquirers or aqua hires on the
one hand, which are largely about
getting talent and hackqua hires with an
H that are about at least ostensibly
avoiding antitrust scrutiny. So if
you're Nvidia and you want to hackwhire,
say Poolside, you're you're going the
Hackquire route rather than just doing
an honest to goodness either asset
acquisition or uh or conventional
acquisition of Poolside because you you
want to argue no actually we're just a
licency of Poolside rather than the
acquirer. No, we're leaving a
competitive open-source model layer blah
blah blah. This is not tying blah blah
blah. That that's the argument and
principle for acquisition.
>> Gotcha. I got a very specific answer to
that too. You remember the windsurf
deal, you know, of course that of
course. Um, so here's the here's the
constraint. So the the FTC is very very
friendly to acquisitions right now. Uh,
and and things tend to move quickly and
easily. On the other hand, the timeline
for AI companies is so short that the
statutory 30-day review alone is like a
lifetime.
>> And and you know, all these mega
companies like a big one like Nvidia is
always going to get a second look, which
is usually 60 90 days. So you're like,
"Forget it. Let me just slap together
any type of deal that doesn't need that
regulatory review and just help, you
know, train the freaking billion dollar
model or $6 billion model. That's all I
need. Let's go." And then they can, you
know, close the deal like Elon did with
Curser. Close the deal many months
later, uh, after an HSR review and after
the 90 days or, you know, sometimes it's
even longer than that, but there's a
statutory 30 days that they just can't
get around. And that's
>> you're smirking over there. What's up on
you? No, no, I think Dave's got it
exactly right. I think that's what's
going on here. This is just purely
juggling the regulatory um hurdles and
obstacle courses.
>> But going back,
>> there's one little wrinkle on this. So
the remaining company actually has
something called poolside infrastructure
company which is building a 1.2 gawatt
data center which might need GPUs. So
they may use some of the money that they
get for GPUs. Who knows? You know,
>> complicated. The other the other point
here is the verticalization of
companies, right? So I mean XAI SpaceX
AI is the ultimate verticalization out
there today. Uh but here we see uh
Nvidia, we've seen Enthropic and OpenAI
also designing their own chips. Um does
every one of these companies ultimately
become you at least two layers if not
three layers?
>> In other words, does Anthropic get a
space station?
>> No.
>> Or a moon colony? uh you know I think
they'll be the only company left amongst
all the governments. Is that what we
learned? Uh
>> they'll be American GDP. That's why
>> I think probably I mean I I'm asking the
question seriously like does Anthropic
get a moon colony? Yeah, probably. Does
Anthropic get a a pharmaceutical arm?
Yeah. Already. So yes.
>> Yeah.
>> All right. I I think that you've got
actually thinking about our discussion
earlier, you have a split of innovation
versus execution. And so these are the
two model splits that are occurring.
Execution drives the majority of the
economy short-term, innovation longer
term. And the verticalization is ideal
for the execution phase. So if you look
at the architecture of Jalapeno, if you
look at where things are going, like
you're going to get closer and closer to
the silicon, you'll get closer and
closer to the customer and you won't
need much better models than you have
now. Whereas the frontier will be a
different story where you still need to
have very complicated things occurring.
>> All right.
>> Yeah. I I I would maybe uh if I had to
uh I guess extrapolate, I think there is
a probably Don't hold me to this.
There's probably a natural
verticalization at the infra layer. Not
necessarily at the application layers,
but at the infra layer for physics and
other reasons. There are natural reasons
why say a company that offers a frontier
model probably wants to be in the data
center infra business, probably wants to
be in the energy business, probably
wants to be in the satellite business.
These are all like innermost loop type
businesses. Robotics business, there are
such natural synergies among all of the
the different innermost loop stages.
probably there's some natural vertical
integration there.
>> I'm going to move us along here. So,
three stories this week that chronicle
the challenges being faced by the US
closed frontier labs uh who are under
siege from faster cheaper Chinese
openweight alternatives. So, the first
story comes from Moonshot AI, not
related to the Moonshots podcast, the
Chinese lab that's making Kimmy. So,
last week discussed how access to memory
is becoming the real roadblock on all of
this growth. It's not GPUs, it's memory.
Especially in the agentic age. This
week, Moonshot AI released Kimmy linear,
a new architecture that cuts context
memory by 75%
while still delivering 6x faster
decoding for a 1 million token context
window. Uh, Moonshot AI just dropped
this and it's running and in a single
move, uh, an improvement of 75%. So,
that's the first story. Uh the second
story uh on this block comes from the
Financial Times that reports that Fable
5, Anthropic's flag flagship model is
now struggling to attract users. It's
effectively plateaued. And the reason is
simple. Cheaper Chinese ope models are
eating the market from bottom up. And
when the model cost 14 cents per million
tokens compared and delivers 80% of the
capability compared to 15 bucks, the
market chooses the less expensive
option. At least the majority of the
market does. Fable 5 is not losing
because it's bad. It's losing because
it's overpriced relative to the
openweight alternatives. The third
story, then we'll talk about this, is
that Enthropic this week reversed its
data retention policy ahead of its IPO,
letting enterprise customers keep data
on their own cloud infrastructure rather
than anthropic servers. Uh, this move,
you know, handles the biggest objection
that corporate buyers have when adopting
claud. So, I don't think the timing is
accidental. You know, they're about to
go into IPO mode. I think it's predicted
for as early as 6 weeks from now. uh and
the growth requires enterprise adoption
and the enterprise adoption requires
data sovereignty. So gentlemen, three
stories here. Kimmy linear uh you know
uh the challenges that Fable is having
and the changes that Anthropic made on
its data retention and policy. Dave, you
want to jump in first? Well, this is
where we're going to find out if Daario
has what it takes to be a public company
CEO because, you know, he's a he's a
brilliant, good-natured AI researcher
thrust into this. And when he gets
interviewed, he said, "I never expected
to be a CEO at all. Uh, but here I am."
So now he's stuck with this uh missing
revenue numbers because he's embargoing
like the the current policy or the prior
policy was even if you're hosting your
Fable 5 on Amazon Bedrock in a secure
environment, everything still has to go
to anthropic headquarters for 30 days
for us to review and make sure you're
not making a virus or a bomb or
something. And that's the only way this
is safe. So now he's missing revenue
numbers because corporations don't want
to give their proprietary secrets to any
company that they don't know well you
know for 30 days and so they're rushing
to the Chinese models and secure
environments and they're also now you
can get you can get GPT soul also inside
a secure environment where it doesn't
get transmitted to open AI so you can
you can use that too. So, I was like,
"Oh god, corporations hate this, but I
don't want to miss my revenue numbers. I
want to go public." On the other hand, I
really don't think it's safe. I need I
feel like I need to inspect everything
to know that it's safe. So, now he's
he's stuck between a rock and a hard
place. It's a tough place to be. But
being a public company CEO is always
like that. It's really really stressful
and really hard. So, we'll see if he if
he has what it takes to do it.
>> Iman, what do you think of Kimmy Lineer?
Yeah, I mean first we banned the
faster silicon from China. So they built
models to take advantage of cheap DRAM.
Then the DAM became expensive. So then
they figured out better mechanisms of
linear retention of caching and more
more dense models etc. And now um you've
just seen actually uh just a couple of
hours ago this new uh 01 stealth model
that's been tearing up the benchmarks
turned out to be a GLM model served
entirely on Chinese chips with trillions
of tokens a day these new Huawei chips.
So I think you know you'll see the
adoption of these Chinese models and
them moving to where the market is on
different form factors of different
chips and again memory is 50% of all
spending now. It is the scarce resource.
You can't upgrade it. So guess what? In
a couple of months time, at the very
least, given the pace of Chinese models,
they won't need much memory. That's how
fast they innovate. On the fable
uptake, it's entirely a Zero data
retention issue. Like as a corporation,
you cannot leave your data on anthropic
side. And they realize this. But
Anthropic should not IPO.
If you are in the late stages of AGI
now, Anthropic should do a giant
freaking raise like Open did of 120
billion and have a straight shot at AGI.
That's what they should do and they
should stay private like
>> that's a fascinating thought. Yeah. I
mean, why why are they racing to an IPO?
>> It makes absolutely no sense to me. Like
Dario owns 2% of the company as does his
seven co-founders. They don't care about
dilution. They're worth like still 67
billion each and they don't care about
money. They pledged to give away 90% of
it. Why would you IPO? I can see no
reason for that unless they can't
actually privately, which I think they
can.
>> Yeah. Go ahead.
>> I have an answer. They need the capital
to get compute.
>> Well, but but
>> they could raise the capital. I I bet
you people would throw money at a drop.
>> So, I've been talking I've been talking
to investors and Dave, this will be
interesting for your perspective. Nobody
knows how to price this thing because
they don't haven't secured long-term
compute like OpenAI has or that natively
Groc or uh Gemini has. Therefore,
they're this is why the way to our
earlier point, this is why people are
verticalizing because if you're at one
layer and the bottleneck goes down below
you or above you, you're screwed. So,
you have to have access to the whole
layer to stop to have continual
progress.
>> Yeah. So that's
>> but even if they had the money to buy
compute where are they going to buy it
from?
>> There's not enough compute being
manufactured.
>> Wait before we get to that there's a SEM
is right but it's much more specific
than that. Like Daario uh got ripped by
Alex Karp. We showed the video on this
podcast. He got absolutely ripped to
shreds. And Alex Karp is saying look you
cannot give your alpha. You cannot give
your weights to this company anthropic.
You cannot trust them with your
corporate intellectual property. You're
talking about an academic never run
anything before in his life guy taking
your intellectual property and then
preaching to you how the government
should be run in the future. Don't trust
him. So he just ripped him to shreds.
You can't. So Dario's now he can't react
to that by saying, "You know what? I'm
going to delay my IPO and do some
private financing." And like you're
playing right into Alex's hands if you
wuss out on your IPO plans. like he's
just going to reinforce Alex's, you
know, Karp's me message horrifically.
And the board members, like look at the
board members at Anthropic. They've
marked up those venture funds to massive
valuations and use those valuations to
raise new funds. So they're not going to
just sit there and say, "Yeah, Dario,
you know, go do, you know, put it off
indefinitely." That's that's fine. So he
he's like, "This is the stress test for
Daario. He can't he can't just wuss out
right now." And that that signaling
would be terrible.
>> [clears throat]
>> Alex, AWG, your thoughts, please. I'm
sure.
>> Okay. Well, first on on the the race to
IPO, I think there's also a race
element. I think there was a starting
gun a few months ago between SpaceX Open
AI and Anthropic. And I think if I'm
anthropic on top of the arguments that
everyone else here has already raised,
there's a competitive element of you
don't necessarily want to be the last to
IPO. The market wins could change. Right
now, it's a relatively warm and friendly
capital market for IPO. So to the extent
there's a window for raising the largest
IPO sum in human history, I think you go
for it. But to the earlier points uh in
lightning round succession, Kimmy
linear, we've known about Kimmy linear
attention since last fall, I think it's
it's suggestive, as I've suggested in
the past, ship of thesis style transform
architecture is getting incrementally
replaced piece by piece. It's
interesting in so far as it's a
successful linear architecture. Many
have tried to linearize the infamously
quadratic attention mechanism. Looks
like KLA may be one of the first at
least openly linearized attention or
quasillinearized. There's a recurrence
mechanism in there as well. So that's
kind of interesting. We've known about
that for a while. Fable 5 struggling.
That is interesting because I I've made
the point on the pod in the past that
Open AAI made a strategic blunder in
pandering to consumers rather than to
enterprises thinking that consumers
would be hungry users of reasoning
tokens and they just weren't. The the
consumers didn't know what to do with
all of these shiny OpenAI reasoning
tokens, but enterprises did. And then
OpenAI had to do this painful pivot over
to enterprise and turn everything into
codecs and probably delay their IPO as a
result. So Fable 5, which is at least by
my accounting the strongest most
frontiest model in the world right now
to the extent that it's struggling to
generate revenue and uptake. I want to
interpret that. I want to construe that
as the enterprises of the world almost
falling prey to the same thing consumers
with open AI did which is this may maybe
will be construed as victim blaming but
it's not. Our economy isn't worthy. It's
not clever or wealthy or successful
enough on average to know how to use
Fable 5 on average properly. Just like
consumers didn't know how to use
reasoning tokens from open AI and as a
result open AI had to pivot. I think
this is the beginning signs of anthropic
being forced to do some sort of pivot.
It could be radically uh reducing the
the cost of their models. That's one
direction. Or I think the more exciting
model uh the more exciting trajectory is
some new use case getting unlocked in
the next year that actually motivates
the usage of this nosebleleed priced
high end of the frontier which is at the
moment fable 5 or depending on the
reports you read maybe fable 5.1 may be
starting to leak out. And then very
quickly on Anthropic and their data
retention policy. Anthropic was so
clever, I think, in being the first
Frontier Lab from America to enable
their Frontier models to be hosted by
third-party hyperscalers rather than
having to host them themselves. And by
some reporting, 40% of Anthropic's
revenue now comes from Anthropic models
being hosted not by Anthropic, but by
third party cloud hyperscalers. So I I
think this is just another step to
externalizing the hosting of their
model. Yeah, sure it's painful. This
data retention policy I view is largely
security theater. I don't think it's
that valuable in the long term. I don't
think it's useful in the long term. But
starting to move more and more of the
the infra layer over to third parties so
that users of Claude can get Claude
where and when they want on the infra
they want. That's powerful. And you see
now open AI copying Anthropic and doing
that.
>> What do you guys make of the, you know,
the idea that the open source Chinese
models are good enough and at a, you
know, dimminimous fraction of the price
and companies are beginning to shift in
that direction, saying we're not going
to use Fable 5, it's too expensive.
Dave, is that an experience you're
having?
>> Yeah. No, everybody needs the absolute
best AI they can get. You can't go down
a notch, but the Chinese models aren't
down a notch. They're they're absolutely
on the frontier. You won't even notice
the difference in any use case. So, it's
not about trying to use something
inferior at a lower cost. It's about the
they're just as good. So, and and now
they're all good enough to improve
themselves, too. So, if you start a
group within your company that's using
these models, you can start improving it
inside your company if you get the
talent. And and so, that's like a
runaway train, you know? I I I think
that's what's really going on. It's not
it's not compromising to save a few
pennies. It's like, wow, we can control
our own destiny and be on the frontier
at the same time.
>> I mean, I don't think it's a few
pennies, right? Like Fable scores 60 on
the artificial analysis benchmark. The
new GLM model flash that dropped today
scores 57 and it is like 100 times
cheaper.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. one
>> which which is I think is really
important because you know the when you
deploy these things the cost benefit is
so high that you might say well I don't
even care about the cost but then you
say oh wait if I use the Chinese version
I can have a thousand or you know this
is why the swarm is such a big deal you
can afford five or 10,000 concurrent
Chinese operators instead of one
anthropic
>> well I think it's like it's like hiring
a specialist you know like super genius
versus a bunch of really smart people.
And sometimes you're not smart enough to
ask the super genius the right
questions.
>> Yeah.
>> Because maybe I'm not smart enough to
ask Fable the right questions, but I'm
just about smart enough to ask GPT 5.6
the right questions. Right.
>> But also, you know, that analogy is
perfect because people misuse their
context window horribly, and I do too.
Everybody does. But if you actually
optimize the context window with the
Chinese model, you'll get a smarter
answer than if you're sloppy using a
fable model. And so, you know, if you
just put a little energy into your
internal org design and optimize your
use and, you know, then you can have
thousands and thousands of these for,
you know, a very low cost. And that's
that's where the puck is going. I'm not
sure how sustainable this this situation
is. I I almost want to analogize it now
to uh US importing generic drugs from
Canada. the the drugs get invented in
the US, they get manufactured cheaply in
Canada, and then at least historically,
it's been the case that that you could
get American drugs more cheaply from
Canada by by importing on or off label
than you could from American drugs. I I
think the situation may be somewhat
analogous here where these are US
models, US reasoning traces. You see
Chinese labs benefiting legally or
illegally from the reasoning traces,
from interacting with US models. And
then just in the past 48 hours, we start
to see stories of Chinese labs trying to
strike partnerships with US hyperscalers
to host the Chinese labs models on US
infra but with a revshare from the
inference costs going back to the
Chinese front tier lab. So this is a
case where US does whatever innovation
is necessary data or post- training or
whatever that there's a distillation
maybe over to China. China sells it back
to us but then we're using our own infra
against ourselves at inference time
against the training time. I think it's
it's a perverse bind that we find
ourselves in analogous to Chinese drug
imports or sorry Canadian drug imports.
All right, I'm not sure the Canadian
drug import analogy holds very much
longer given what's going on, but let's
leave that aside.
>> Yeah, it holds until about a year ago.
>> I'm going to move us to a fun story on
the dating front. So, a Berkeley startup
called Ditto is playing Cupid. Uh, Ditto
is an app or a AI that has no feed, no
swiping, no infinite scroll. uh you fill
out a values questionnaire and then
every Wednesday at 7 p.m. a text arrives
with a match as well as a place and a
time for you to meet your date. That's
the entire product. You show up and see
if the magic happens. Thus far, 160,000
college students have signed up. Uh it's
already produced 80,000 dates. The app
does what Tinder and Hinge refuse to do.
It removes choice. The entire dating
industry is built on the premise that
more options are better. But Ditto
believes that too many options lead to,
you know, decision fatigue, analysis
paralysis, and then AI is the cure. The
app does not ask you for a choice. It
chooses for you. You know, this is sort
of the old style matchmaker agent. You
know, a yenta if you would, and it seems
to be working. Uh, Seem, you know, you
and I are are both married, but you
know, it seems like it'd be a fun thing
to go out and try.
>> What are your thoughts?
>> Two, so two or three things. I think
this applied to non-dating would be
really profound and we're actually
looking at doing something like that for
business connections. Uh but I think
this is powerful because AI isn't adding
an interface, it's deleting the
interface, right? Tinder optimized
searching and connections and so on, but
this makes the searching unnecessary.
And I think that's really a powerful
user interface experience where people
are going to go let the AI figure it out
and then I'll do the connection and see
if there's chemistry there or not, which
you have to do anyway. By the way, let's
note as a scarcity to abundance
paradigm. When we were all growing up,
sex had a scarcity paradigm. With
Tinder, sex became abundant. Where the
hell was that in our 20s is the obvious
question. But you have to deal with that
abundance in a different way. So, this
is the really fascinating thing. I'll
watch this very carefully to see where
this goes.
>> Yeah. This is the abundance thesis
applied to to dating. Uh Dave, what do
you make of it? Is this a company you
would have backed?
>> Oh, god. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Absolutely.
But I think this is a stepping stone to
AI helping you manage your life and your
choices in general.
>> Bingo.
>> Which I think is going to be if it's
done right, it's going to be one of the
greatest boounds to mental health in
world history. If it's left to
manipulate you, it's going to be
horrible because it's such a great
salesperson. So this is a good a good
test case, you know, are we going to
manage it well? Is it going to lead you
to the right person? Is it going to try
and help you? Or is it going to sell you
on something that you don't want? So
>> yeah, I've always said, you know, in the
future, you know, advertising model's
gone because your AI knows you so well.
He's like, like, please just buy me the
stuff I need. I don't want to. I'm in
decision fatigue. I'm in data overwhelm.
Just take care of it for me. Immod, your
thoughts?
>> Yeah, I I think there was a Black Mirror
episode where, you know, for dating, you
just sent your digital twins and then
they did a bunch of dates just to test
it out in like 2 milliseconds so you
could tell whether or not you matched.
It kind of again it feels like you're
heading towards that but people are
going to get to a point where it'll be
like you can't argue with your AI it
knows best right all watched over by
machines of loving grace and you've got
to be quite careful about that because
you know it does take away a little bit
from your intrinsic humanity if you
outsource your cognition and connection
in that way. Um, but you know, again,
you're kind of feeling it already like
uh with how much of your stuff you
offload to these things. And I've been
getting mad at like some of the
colleagues and others like, you know,
they're doing really good, but they
started to slip into trusting the AI too
much,
>> you know, like sending something like
this is human.
>> I I think this is such an important
point. There's a bigger pattern here
where AI is becoming the trusted
intermediary between
uh individuals interfacing with
overwhelming abundance right you're
going to need that trust and interface
and the question is do you want to
outsource that trust by the way to your
yenta comment Peter uh the Indian
matchmaking industry is profoundly about
to be disrupted by this because you
could detail the cast the clothing
requirements and salary requirements and
boom off you go for the matches so this
is going to be really interesting apply
to that world
>> uh an exponential organization come on
[clears throat] diagn
one.
>> Alex, I think you're the only one
amongst us not married. So, uh, you
know, would you try this out?
>> No. I I think this is why we can't have
nice things. I think this is why. Have
you seen the Ditto body count detector?
Do you even know what I'm talking about?
>> No. Tell me.
>> Okay. So, the the Ditto body count
detector. This is I I would characterize
as a politely suboptimal use of scarce
reasoning tokens is a tool that Ditto
released that uses, I'll quote from
their website, 478 facial points and 52
micro expressions over 5 seconds to
estimate how many sexual partners a
person has had. This is where the
reasoning tokens are going. This is low.
Seriously, it's called the Ditto AI body
count detector. Folks can check it out.
Th this is I I view as a sub-optimal use
of reasoning tokens when we could be, as
you and I wrote, Peter, we could be
solving everything. Yes, we could be
solving everything and instead we're
doing body count detection. So, this one
gets a thumbs down for me.
>> All right. Well, you know, the reality
is that most people on these dating apps
are looking at, you know, simply the
external parameters of the individual.
Are they handsome? Are they beautiful?
Uh I I think part of it is how honest
are you on the questionnaire? Uh and you
know matchmaking does work you know
throughout time and culture in across
all cultures. Some of the longest
lasting marriages come from being
matched because it's going beyond just
your initial hormonal response to the
individual. Uh and I think there's
something there. Whether or not it has
sufficient data to actually, you know,
align two people accurately is a
different thing. Uh, but I think there's
something there. But I do agree, Dave,
that this applies to so many different
areas. And and Sem, I know at at the
Abundance Summit, right? We have 600
CEOs. Um, and we're, by the way, we're
now 90% full for Abundance 2027. If
you're interested, you can go to
Abundance 360. Um, matching the CEOs,
matching the entrepreneurs there is one
of the most important things we do. uh
and using AI to create those matches
because randomly bumping into the right
person among a a group of 600 people in
five days is tough. So there is there is
a value proposition to be had there.
>> Social discovery I I do think is quite
valuable if it's for socially productive
or economically productive purposes.
Social discovery for body count
detection. I mean again this reminds me
of Hot or Not back in the the early
Facebook days. I I just think we could
be aiming so much higher as a
civilization than AI for this.
>> Yeah. Listen, you know, the divorce rate
in the United States is 50%. Which is
crazy. And I think, you know, helping
you discover the right person. Now, the
parameters it uses may not be right, but
if it were possible uh to help you find
the best person, the best match for you,
there's massive value, societal value in
that. Uh that's my feeling. I don't know
if you guys
>> Yeah, I'd love to know, Alex, how you
reconcile um this is a a waste of
tokens. Uh we should be solving a
disease.
>> Not a waste, a suboptimal use.
>> Okay. Okay. Because because one of the
terms you've coined in this great
revolution is patriot.
What is that thing?
>> Patricia Musa.
>> Yeah. You can't even say it. [laughter]
>> No, no, that is
Patricia Musa.
>> Okay.
>> Alex loves neologisms. If you haven't
seen it, he's publishing new terminology
for the singularity almost every day.
>> Yeah. Go ahead.
>> You do you do need a token budget for
for that concept, you know. So, how do
how do you reconcile those two?
>> That's what happens once we have a
leisure class that can afford tokens too
cheap to meter, which we don't yet have.
So, may maybe the way I reconcile to
make you happy, Dave, is I'd say save
the body count detection until after
we've solved everything. At at that
point, do as much body count detection
as you like.
>> I like that. I like that view. I think
once you've solved basically all major
diseases, that's probably a good time to
start.
>> All right.
>> The line of the song is that once the
day had been solved, the day hasn't yet
been solved.
>> Okay. All right, guys. I'm I'm going to
move us on, but it's a it's a
fascinating concept and uh I I hope
Ditto works and there are many happy
relationships that come out of it.
>> This episode is brought to you by
Blitzy, autonomous software development
with infinite code context. Blitzy uses
thousands of specialized AI agents that
think for hours to understand [music]
enterprise scale code bases with
millions of lines of code. Engineers
start every development sprint with the
Blitzy platform, bringing in their
development requirements. The Blitzy
platform provides a plan, then generates
and pre-ompiles code for each task.
Blitzy delivers 80% or more of the
development work autonomously while
providing a guide for the final 20% of
human development work required to
complete the sprint. Enterprises are
achieving a 5x engineering velocity
increase when incorporating Blitzy as
their preIDE development tool, pairing
it with their coding co-pilot of choice
to bring an AI native SDLC into their
org. Ready to 5x your engineering
velocity? Visit blitzy.com to schedule a
demo and start building with Blitzy
today.
>> One more AI story before we move on to
robotics. Um, and uh, it's a Wall Street
Journal article that confirms what all
of us are feeling that AI is making us
work harder at a level like never
before. I I joke people are talking
about a three and four day work week and
I've discovered a 9 and 10 day work
week. So according to the Wall Street
Journal, increased productivity from AI
agents is creating more work for humans,
not less. The agents produce more
output, which requires more review, more
decisions, more direction, and more
human judgment per unit time. You know,
the founder used to manage five tasks,
now manages 50 agent outputs. The
bottleneck has shifted from execution to
judgment. The humans have become the
bottleneck because the agents produce
too much work for us lowly humans to
evaluate. So this is a bizarre
implication of abundance. Uh more
intelligence produces more output which
requires more human direction which
produces more value which requires more
work. So the work is not disappearing
it's changing character from execution
to judgment. See over to you pal.
>> This is Jeban's paradox for human
cognition right we thought AI would
reduce workload instead. In fact it
increased the the amount of work that is
worth attempting. I will go to a little
history here. When I first did the exo
book, Peter, you and I did that
together. It was three years of hell.
Second book was two and a half years of
hell. Third book was 6 months of a lot
of joy, but damn overload on the
cognitive workload. Right? So when you
get this kind of AI
slop in a sense for human cognition,
really judgment and attention become
absolutely paramount. So this becomes
what we've done is essentially if 10
agents are reporting to a founder we've
reinvented middle management it's inside
your own brain right so this is this is
it's going to cause a huge problem
because you can't have machines
operating in machine speed and requiring
human approval on on that so I'm
actually facing this from all the stuff
I'm trying to do today you may be seeing
the same thing with skippy so we need
the better next breakthroughs need you
need to be better delegation permission
escalation crashes and we're actually
designing that BCI maybe at the
individual level but you know this is
something we're actually seeing live as
we do that pilot program where we work a
bunch of companies through this process
it's requiring a whole new threshold of
escalation thresholds governance etc etc
because companies need to decide what
the machines may decide autonomously and
what they want to manage later what it's
audited what genuinely needs a human
otherwise we're creating a totally crazy
h future where AI's going to be working
like 24/7 and humans are going to be
obligated to work 24/7 to navigate that
and keep pace of that. Right. So more
capability more it does but more
capability doesn't mean more freedom but
but I'm actually I'm burning the candle
16s right now. I'm loving it but I'm not
sure how long I can last at this pace
and you guys aren't helping I will say.
[laughter]
>> So can I just ask for you know Dave you
know Em and Alex is it the same for all
of you working harder than ever? God.
Yeah, absolutely. And and I'll tell you
what, you got to savor the moment
because you know, Ahmad and Alex will
tell you it's not going to last forever.
And I you know what's really frustrating
to me is actually I've been recruiting
some incredibly talented people for
quantum AI and we lost an MIT core 61
guy who just decided he's going to go to
the Princeton PhD program and like do
you listen to Ahmad and Alex you know
and like you you guys have collectively
like a 100 degrees and would you advise
anyone right now to go into a PhD
program and miss the singularity like no
of course not but it's frustrating to to
watch that happen because this moment
we're in right now You can master a
thousand AIs, 10,000 AIs, and you're the
most valuable you'll ever be in human
history right now because they won't do
anything productive without your help.
Uh, but a year or two from now, they may
say, "Yeah, I don't need your help. You
know, sorry, you know, don't need you
anymore.
>> Get out of the way."
>> So, yeah, work your ass off right now
because it may be the last chance that
you have to actually be extremely
valuable. So, I'm just savoring it. I'm
working harder than ever by far, but
savoring every minute of it. And I tell
you, working with the eyes is genuinely
fun, too. It's not like I'm, you know,
moving boxes around or or grinding it
out in a corn field. You know, this is
like really, really fun. You're
discovering the future.
>> It is fun.
>> It's a blast.
>> A friend of mine likes to say the Stone
Age didn't end for a lack of stones. I I
think this era that we find ourselves in
is probably pretty brief. I know I'm
getting approximately no sleep at at
this point largely because almost all of
my time is spent supervising and
steering fleets of agents and I think
this is a window. I don't think this
will continue very much longer at most
maybe one or two or 3 years at that
point the AIS will be sufficiently self-
steering that the role for humans in
being kneedeep in steering large fleets
I think probably erodess to to a
dimminimous role. So, isn't that an
argument for just like, you know, lay
down, relax, enjoy yourself for three
years, and then jump in three years from
now?
>> No, it's an argument for work your tail
off for three years and then go lie on
the beach.
>> I mean, if nothing else motivates you,
every year millions of people die
needlessly and if we just get, you know,
three months shaved off that timeline by
working our asses off, millions of
people will exist forever that otherwise
wouldn't exist.
>> Beautifully said. If
>> that doesn't motivate you, Amad, you got
to put a clip in here, too. This is the
most important thing we've ever
recorded. So, What what are your
thoughts on this?
>> No, I mean like the amount of leverage
you can do per unit of your attention
now is more than has ever been. And I
think as Alex said, it probably ever
will be. Like you're approaching the
last human discoveries. You're
approaching the last point of being able
to deploy and control these things. And
I think again like you have a limited
focused attention budget. That's why
you're getting tired. Maybe to try and
coin theology maybe it's cognithology
you know cognitive lethargy that we're
facing here from my own side you know
I've written now like two books in the
last year I've done a massive amount of
research and I've been in a flow with
hundreds of agents but like last week I
stopped I couldn't do any more research
cuz I had to go and take this out to the
world now so we're doing like a big
funding round we're launching lots of
new things we'll be releasing all the
research finally and I turned off my
agents that were doing all the research.
Like I've set them on to auto mode. No
more mad stuff and they're coming up
with things still, but like I can only
read it once a week. I've actually made
it so I can't do it. And I think you can
shift between these modes of work
because you can't be on all the time
because it does burn you out. But at the
same time, if you get in the right flow,
then you can do more than you've ever
done before. And like I said, I can't
imagine like I would say on this podcast
straight up, don't do a PhD. If you're
thinking about doing a PhD, don't do
one. Peter Theal paid all these people
not to do PhDs.
>> Well, not to do college degrees, let
alone
>> PhDs. I would say you not even do a
college degree. Like what will you get
out of it right now? You will go and you
will learn a very specific thing when
you should be learning agency. Like a
fellowship of the type of people who do
that will go way bigger than they've
ever gone before. And you know parents
might kind of complain and things but
show them what you create. Gather
people, humans and agents.
A skeptic would say, "All right, Amhod,
you went where? Oxford, as I recall.
[laughter]
Alex, you you you went where? Harvard
and MIT. Dave, you went where? MIT?
Peter, you went where? MIT? Harvard?"
And and so on. Like, okay. So, you're
pulling the you're pulling the vertical
mobility ladder up behind you and it's
fine to tell everyone else who's just
coming up, h don't bother with higher
education, don't bother with
credentialitis, just go off and do your
startup. And yet, we didn't follow that.
>> We didn't have that time. We did.
>> It was a different type. It was a
different type that just makes you more
credible in what you're saying than I
>> I would actually say I think
undergraduates still a lot of fun and
you don't really have
>> Elon said this. It's a social experience
>> but
>> it's adult daycare.
>> It's adult daycare. So, it's actually
great for using massive amounts of
agents. PhDs though, I don't get, you
know, especially like I I feel sorry for
I talked to a bunch of my buddies who
are math PhDs and a couple of them had
like problems solved in the recent
batch. Like they don't even know what
they're going to do. Every verifiable
domain PhD now is under massive threat.
Why would you even do it or even
consider it? I agree. I was speaking
>> I was speaking a few days ago to a
government funded AI for physics center
filled with PhDs uh current PhDs and
recent PhDs in physics. And I I leveled
with them. I said physics is cooked and
you should probably be reconsidering all
of your career trajectories and consider
any advice to the contrary. Give that a
a double think as it were before you
just go and follow some zombie pattern.
Well, I think this is the most important
conversation we've had we've had yet. We
spoke to them this and I spoke the heck
out of them.
>> Well, getting people to think is the
most important. Um, you know, why are
you doing a PhD? A lot of people are
doing a PhD because they're they told
their mom and dad they're going to do it
or their sibling did it or they thought
that was what they needed in life. And I
think
>> or actually in a lot of cases about 5
years ago before anyone knew the
singularity was coming, they started
working their ass off toward that. and
and you've been working so hard in for
so long and then you get in and it's
like I I got in but now now the idea
that suddenly it's irrelevant [snorts]
or you shouldn't be doing it is so hard
to take after you work so hard to get
there but you got to pivot. You got to
you got to just recognize the moment
>> get into your Stanford PhD and say okay
I I checked that box and now I'm gonna
jump into a company. Um, oh well. It's
uh it's important for people to realize
the world is very different than it was
before. All right, I'm going to move us
forward. Uh, this is a conversation
we've had before. Uh, two stories on the
data center debacle. The first story is
about public sentiment. So, a year ago
and then again this month, a year later,
Heatmap News pulled Americans about data
centers. A year ago, Americans were
split 43 to 42 on whether they oppose
data centers being built near them.
Today, the opposition has risen to 75%
with 61% saying they are strongly
opposed. Also this week, Senator Bernie
Sanders once again called for a
nationwide moratorum. The second story
is about a post on X that went viral
about data center waterm. We've talked
about this on the pod before. Here's the
data on on people uh against data
centers. It's been increasing uh you
know almost I guess it's a linear
increase but it's going to asmtote near
100%. Um and the post on the water
center the water data use um the data
center water use uh it was pretty
damning. So here are the numbers. Data
centers are at 627 million gallons per
day. Sounds like a big number, but
compare it to, you know, golf courses at
two billion, three times as much, or
power plants at 133 billion, or growing
cattle at 137 billion. You know, the
fact matter is that, you know, the tech
industry is a trust problem. And I I
think we've talked about this before. If
I were a hyperscaler building a data
center, uh I would do this very
different. I would promise, you know,
we're going to put education programs in
the schools. We're going to, you know,
make the cost of energy in your
community lower than it is today. And
we're going to make these data centers
not look like ugly boxes. We're going to
make them look like cathedrals. I mean,
spending an extra 10%. Uh, I don't know
why that's not going on right now.
Honestly, don't.
>> My worry is that that wouldn't help. My
fear is that this isn't because people
think data centers are unsightly or uh
unesthetic. My my concern is that it's
being overly politicized in part through
the worst case scenario which would be
foreign interference. There are a number
of US adversaries who would love nothing
more than to slow down America's data
center buildout. We talk about at least
one of them all the time on this pod. So
my concern would be that we look back in
a year or two and see that some quantum
of this opposition to data center
construction is actually the result of
popular sentiment being stoked by
foreign adversaries.
>> Okay, agreed, Alex. But um why isn't the
you know you can counterveail that when
I was on with with Michael Katios I said
why isn't the White House getting out in
front of this and you know because it's
an issue that is gaining steam. people
can see this. The second thing is you
can counter that by saying, listen, like
this is what Zuck said in this video
last week, right? We're going to, you
know, give you better schools. We're
going to give you better access to uh to
jobs. We're going to be a positive
contributor to the community. You know,
you can get to a point where having a
data center is such an advantage to your
community that people are going to say,
I don't, you know, that's that's false
news. Here's the facts. Cheaper energy,
right? uh
>> the pro the problem though is that in in
the US way of doing things the decision
of whether to site a data center or not
ends up being a local decision not a
national decision whereas in China China
can just declare okay the east is going
to be responsible for data the west is
going to be responsible for comput and
energy and we're going to build this
national scale grid for combining
compute data and energy together and
poof you're the CCP and you get to
centrally command the whole economy In
in the US, we have a different system
where individual local municipalities
and states get to say what they do and
do not want their land used for. And we
end up in the system that's far easier
if you're a foreign adversary, worst
case scenario, to polarize and to shut
data centers out of terrestrial
deployment.
>> But this is false data. There's this is
an outrage cycle in social media. This
is people
>> shocked that foreign interference would
leverage false data. Shocked.
Wait, let me let me say a couple things
about this.
>> Can I?
>> Yeah, please.
>> Okay,
>> Mr. Wum.
>> So, we have a problem where our
information systems reward compelling
narratives over evidence. And this data
center thing is the heart of that. And
it's a problem that's been building up
over decades with the use of social
media. We are not evidentiary based in
the US at all. This is really a big
challenge because we're totally
narrative driven and not evidentiary
driven at all. We decide what the story
is and then we go looking for facts that
support it. Okay, data centers are a
great hobby horse for this. Uh this is
happening everywhere. We've gone from
say 50 years ago, show me the evidence
and I'll form an opinion to I have an
opinion now show me the evidence that
confirms it. and therefore and that's
amplified radically with social media
because nuance has no viral coefficient
like this this just doesn't actually
work. So this is a very difficult
problem to solve actually doubly
enhanced by the interference that I'm
absolutely clear is happening and I'm
with Alex on this one. The problem is
we're making national policy based on
these stupid innuendos and memes rather
than measurement. You cannot run an
advanced civilization with this. This is
a massively big issue, a huge
opportunity to make humanity go from
scarcity to abundance and measure it,
compare it, put it in context, fix the
externality, but don't legislate with a
story in your head, which is what the
hell is going on right now. It's a
completely disastrous problem we have.
It's goes to the cognitive issue of the
US.
>> So, let me hear something really really
cool.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh, I don't know if you ever met Rob
Fischer. He was the president of Link
Studio for years. He he left to start a
data center company a few years ago and
they're killing it. It's called
provocative AI.
>> The data center is actually water
negative and carbon negative.
>> There you go.
>> It's so cool. So, you know, it's like
it's doing its own carbon capture using
waste heat, you know, running off
nuclear power mostly from Seabbrook, New
Hampshire. And it captures more carbon
than the entire loop produces. And they
said, "Oh, you know what? We can
actually use just the humidity
accumulating because of the temperature
gradient to create more water than we
consume and just use our own dripping
water. Then nobody can complain. We're
not we're actually water negative and
carbon negative. That's really it's
really cool.
>> And I think I saw
>> it shows you how little water they
actually use.
>> Alex, wasn't there a story recently
about Nvidia's new chips and and new
data center structures that are actually
utilizing less water now?
>> Yeah. Well, there's there's news flash,
there's no water in low Earth orbit. So,
that's the end game. I I I think just
cut the the water nonsense out. This is
only forcing all of these new data
center deployments to sun-synchronous
orbit. We might as well just get it over
with.
>> Yeah. I mean, how how intelligent was
Elon's move? Prophetic. Um
>> I think it was opportunistic. I think he
he laid all the infra for Mars and then
opportunistically and timely pivoted to
sun-synchronous orbit and the Dyson
swarm because he read the tea leaves.
>> Amazing. Uh
>> can I say something more? Can I just say
one more thing just if I lift up a level
to the to the rationale and the
foundation of why this podcast exists to
reach evidence we need to reach
abundance. We need an evident
evidentiary foundation in our culture.
Otherwise, every new technology is going
to be strangled by the narratives that
go viral before the evidence can spread.
And this is the fundamental foundational
problem we have with civilization. As
Alex said, this is why we can't have
nice things.
>> I reckon we should just rename them.
Let's call them intelligence foundaries
or call them compute citadels. You know,
>> change the narrative. It's got a
branding problem.
>> It's a branding problem. Again, this is
not a factual thing.
the funniest tweets I saw recent. Okay,
>> I have a better one. AI churches.
>> Yeah, a computer says beats AI church.
Come on.
>> Fine.
>> Sorry. Go ahead.
>> I'm moving us along here. All right,
let's jump into the world of robotics.
So, uh, for the longest time, the
economics of Whimo versus CyberCab have
been devastating. You know, Elon
projected that a cyber cab will cost
about $30,000. that's what he said he'd
sell them at um for the vehicle and the
sensor hardware compared to Whimo's Gen
5 Jaguar which costs about $300,000.
200K for the vehicle, 100K for the full
autonomous driving hardware package. In
other words, Whimo is coming in or has
been coming in at 10 times as a
disadvantage to CyberCap. This week, uh
Whimo announced a significant redesign
and cost savings. They announced details
around their custom 5nanometer chip that
processes camera, LAR, and radar data in
real time. I love this. At one
quadrillion operations per second, we've
gone past trillions. We're at
quadrillions already. Helping Yeah. help
uh helping slash their sixth generation
autonomous driving hardware costs from
115,000 to 20,000. At the same time,
Whimo unveiled the Ohhigh vehicle, uh, a
purposebuilt robo taxi minivan designed
by Chinese EV maker Ziker. Uh, the Ohigh
cost $75,000 per vehicle compared to the
$200,000 for the generation 5 Jaguar.
Uh, it's 42% fewer sensors, 13 cameras,
and four LARs compared to 29 cameras and
five LARs. Yeah. And remember, you know,
Elon made the the point years ago that
if a human driver can drive with just
one eye, uh, you know, you should be
able to do all the driving with just
visual sensors. Also, in relating news,
Nvidia this week uh gave permission for
Tesla, Uber, and Whimo to simultaneously
begin operations in Las Vegas. So, let's
watch a quick video about the new Whimo.
I had a chance to ride in it yesterday.
Uh, it's a it's a pretty cool vehicle.
Um, kind of uh not as sexy as the gold
cyber cab, but take a look
>> what Wayo calls its sixth generation
driver, the hardware [music] and
software system that actually does the
driving. Combine that lower cost Chinese
hardware with this [music] new interior
tech, which the company says was
designed to cut sensor cost while
improving performance, and the math
starts to move in Whimo's favor in a way
that it hadn't previously. Now, the last
system running in the Jaguar fleet had
significantly more sensors. The new one
[music] uses 13 cameras, four LAR, and
six radars, and Whimo says it performs
better. The company switched to 17
megapixel cameras, a major jump from
[music] the previous specs. Higher
resolution means the system can see more
with fewer cameras. [music]
They slashed the total sensor count by
more than 40%, so cost is down and
capabilities are up. The new system also
builds heaters, wipers, and sprayers
[music] into the sensor pods directly,
which helps them clear snow, ice, and
road grime.
>> All right. Well, some good moon by
Whimo. Uh I've been using it pretty
regularly here. It's much cheaper than
Uber. Uh Alex, let's go to you first.
>> Okay. So, uh venting some pain here. So,
Jaguar, uh owned by an Indian company
now, but was doing its manufacturing in
the UK.
>> Yeah. but was doing its manufacturing
largely for Jaguars in the UK. Look
behind the headline. The we careful what
we wish for with uh whoever here is
suggesting that Google should just
switch over to fine-tuning Chinese
models. News flash, Google, Whimo,
Alphabet uh are switching over to using
and OEMing Chinese hardware in order to
achieve Whimo objectives. I would rather
see the West use a western hardware
stack rather than just white labeling
Chinese hardware. That's somewhat
disappointing. It's also kind of
interesting if if you look uh underneath
at the the overall chip supply chain
that they're using. It seems like
they're moving away from Broadcom.
They're they're vertically integrating,
which is I I think a theme that we were
speaking about here earlier. Whimo is
maybe Whimo wants its own space station
at this point. Whimo is is getting its
own chips. It's OEMing Chinese hardware
at the hardware layer. Maybe it's it's
playing footsie with Uber for the moment
for distribution, but probably wants to
own its own distribution in the long
term. I know whenever I use Whimo, I'm
not using or engaging with Whimo via
some aggregator app. I interact directly
with Whimo. So, I I think we're starting
to see honest to goodness vertical in
integration here. and wouldn't also be
surprised as Alphabet Whimo is starting
to drive costs down in this case I guess
by white labeling Chinese hardware.
There's an interesting historic rhyme
with Tesla which started with high-end
Roadster and has been pushing down costs
right up until they hit the autonomy
barrier at which point remember the the
Tesla Model 2 that was supposed to
launch but never did. that was going to
be the highly vaunted $25,000 vehicle
never launched because Tesla hit
autonomy instead and below some
threshold in car price. Maybe doesn't
make sense to to sell cheaper cars. It
makes more sense to just get out of car
sales entirely and offer hosted autonomy
platforms. I think we're going to start
to see Whimo at some point in order to
drive the cost down. they'll just ditch
all third-party vendors and they turn
into a white label sort of a Dell for
for Chinese hardware or maybe American
hardware and their focus is entirely on
software again.
>> Yeah, the vertical integration is is
completely unprecedented in history.
It's something it's a byproduct of the
singularity that I don't think I fully
grasped until now that we're living it.
But if you look at the largest companies
in history, you know, you'd have Exon
Mobile doing oil, you'd have IBM doing
mainframe computers, GE, where my dad
was doing nuclear reactors and toasters,
but they did different things. Now, all
11 of the Magna Mobster companies are
building AI chips and building AI models
and building data centers, every one of
[clears throat] them. So, they're all
colliding into vertically integrated
super companies and and they're just
doing the entire stack.
>> And robots next.
>> And robots. going to build robots.
>> And meanwhile, TSMC is a sitting duck.
TSMC is waiting to be verticalized.
>> Isn't that amazing?
>> It's like the the lynch pin to this
entire thing, and it's sitting there not
doing anything
>> right across the straight of Taiwan
ready to start World War II at a
moment's notice.
>> Y
>> IO, do you ever see these vehicles
coming to Europe?
>> Uh, yeah. We're starting to see Whimos
in London, and I think the regulation
actually be largely positive for them.
But I was having dinner today with
Yanuisa, Deep Tech VC at Lake Motif. And
you know, we're talking about something
interesting like because previously I
said, you know, a Tesla Optimus robot
gets into a truck, opens the door, plugs
itself into the phone char into the
phone charger or the cigarette plug, and
boom, that's trucking job's gone. And I
was like, well, actually, why wouldn't
you have specialist robot drivers?
You know, like you don't need to
retrofit all these cars because you
think about a humanoid robot that's
walking around in the real world versus
one that sits in a cockpit driving a
car. It's so much simpler. And I did a
bill of materials. I'm like, that's like
$6,000 with the actuators and
everything. And so I was like, "Oh crap,
this could actually happen a lot
quicker."
>> Yeah.
>> The other side of it is that you fully
vertically integrate. So Xiai just
announced a Xiaomi car. They've gone
from mobile phones to cars with a fully
dark factory. And so of course you'd
vertly integrate if you have a fully
dark factory. So I kind of feel like
there these kind of two things that are
coming. But like I said, I really got
thinking about this humanoid driver
robot.
>> I love that idea. It's the first use
case for a humanoid robot with two arms
and two legs. I've yet seen so
I will I will yield to you sir.
[laughter]
>> Yeah. So Palmer lucky I on the podcast I
did with Palmer uh we talked about
humanoid robots and whether he was going
to build them. He said, you know, uh the
use case for for these in the military
right now is getting into jeeps or
getting into uh nuclear silos and
replacing the humans and sitting at the
desk and not changing out the interface
hardware. Just create a humanoid robot
that can interface what with what a
human did before. So that makes makes a
lot of sense.
It's vaudevilian again like lack of
imagination but also the ergonomics are
such that we're incentivized to deploy
humanoid robots initially into these
human use cases but I I'm still pretty
bullish for what it's worth for the next
10 years on the humanoid form factor.
See
>> well I think you you've kind of got two
things here like one is full vertical
integration. The other is human-shaped
holes with humans humanoids in it. All
right, I'm going to move us on to the
next story.
>> Wait, I just
>> I just want to respond, Alex, very
quickly. One of the funniest things I
think I've ever heard you say, Alex, a
couple of podcasts ago when I talked
about why do we have humanoid? You said,
"Oh my god, Phil, the why the
self-loathing." It was so funny. So, I
just love that. So, I just want to
reflect back on that.
>> We We love We love our humanoid form
factors.
>> All right. This next story I love. It's
uh you know I love it when a technology
really fits a perfect use case and we
saw that demonstrated this week uh with
a video out of China once again uh with
a hybrid life preserver and drone being
demonstrated. So these autonomous rescue
drones can fly at 30 mph uh covering you
know up to almost 2 miles landing on
water providing flotation for two 80 kg
adults. It saves lives. We're talking
about a drone that flies at 30 mph
compared to a human lifeguard swimming
at 2 mph. I love this product. Let's
take a look at the quick video here. Uh,
and it's like, wow. Best use of a drone
I've seen.
Pretty
amazing guys. So I thought this was
fantastic for a couple of reasons,
right? This is compressing time response
time where time equals lives. So this is
so great because autonomous response is
so much more interesting than remote
control in this context for this type of
use case. these type of applications
that can you do more for public
acceptance of AI than any like chatbot
benchmark whatever it's such a great use
case I love this
>> yeah Alex
>> yeah so another one of my neisms was the
broken whimos theory people who haven't
seen this may remember from the '9s the
broken windows theory most famously
associated with Rudy Giuliani and the
purported rehabilitation of the streets
of New York City the idea was at the
time that if there were broken windows
that uh was either a proxy for or even
causally related with broader crime
issues and that you could almost run
this causal relationship in reverse that
if you made sure that there were no
broken windows you could make sure that
crime overall was down or at least that
was the thinking at the time in sub
quadrants in New York City in the '9s
and the early 2000s. Similarly, uh maybe
hopefully slightly better founded. I
I've tried to push the notion of a
broken Whamos theory. Uh the idea being
that if a city or a nation can't deploy
autonomous robots, then they're not
prepared for the singularity. Uh, and I
I see videos like this uh drone [snorts]
life preserver aircraft coming out of
China and I shake my head a bit because
here in Boston we can't even get Whimos
and I raised the subject or attempted to
raise the subject with Mayor Woo a
couple weeks ago dimminimous progress. I
I just think like we're getting lapped
by China at this point.
>> This is what Sam said. This is this is
institutional inertia. This is the you
know the existing uh players blocking
their disruption. This is not a
surprise.
>> Not a surprise but definitely a
disappointment.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. But I think the AI labs were very
late to address PR and realize they need
PR and now they're on it and we'll see
where it goes from here. But you know
the the government reacts to voters. The
voters are anti- everything. anti-data
center, anti-A disruption, anti- job
loss. And that's because the foundation
labs who are now writing documents like
machines of love and grace, you know,
this is the roadmap for how the whole
world should be governed in the age post
AI. Well, okay, but get ahead of your P.
You can't have every voter hating you
while you try to roll out that road map.
So, get ahead of your PR. In China, the
the news is controlled by the central
government. So, they just dictate the
PR. I mean, it's a much easier problem
in the closed world than in the free
world, but at least the AI labs are
aware of it now and that hopefully
they'll get on it and we'll start out
like the the lifeguard is such a
no-brainer.
>> I remember here in Santa Monica when
electric scooters came out uh after a
few weeks, you'd see them hanging from
trees. You'd see them in parts on the
ground. People started hating them. And
then we had the the Whimo fires here uh
back I don't know a year and a half ago.
So, you know, Immod, you said this in
the last pod that these robots on the
streets are going to be made illegal.
I'm curious, when we start seeing figure
robots, uh, you know, we're going to
have Brad Atcock back on the show here.
We should talk about that. Um, and we
start seeing Tesla on the streets, are
people going to like try and capture
these and and hang them from nooes? You
know, I think we're going to have an
interesting uh you know, sort of
collision between those who can afford
these robots and see them walking on the
street uh and those who find them super
valuable for helping them at home. So
stay tuned.
>> I mean, I think you do you will see
lynching of robots and things. You will
see people vandalize them like they
vandalize cars, you know, like stealing
them and all sorts of things. Yeah. I
think Dave, I think the Chinese, it
isn't so much about the control of the
media. They genuinely see them as
useful. You need it for the population
pyramid in China. They've had a
technological leap forward already. I
think that China will produce robots. It
will improve the Chinese way of life
just like the electrical revolution
there for cars is, just like AI
everywhere ubiquitously is. The short
form video is flooding things maybe not
so much. But, you know, China will do
that. And I think China will stop
exporting robots in 5 years.
>> This is what you're right. And I think I
think we we think that a free country or
a free economy, a free Europe,
>> the press can report the truth and
therefore people will get the truth.
>> But if you read what's written in China,
it's actually much more truthful about
technology than what gets published in
the US. So you talk about the water in
the in the data centers. So what's
actually happening is it's backfiring
where the free press, which is starved
for any budget, is starting to publish
garbage. That's that's actually
factually not true. And so the the the
free press is kind of backfiring right
now in the age of AI.
>> Dave, this is what Al Alvin said on
that, right? I mean, he said basically
China has seen a technology revolution
moving so many people into middle class
and they appreciate technology uplifting
them. So they're much more anticipatory
and excited about AI.
>> And if they don't, if they don't,
they'll they'll get invited by the CCP
for tea. So we'll never hear from them.
>> I'm not pro CCP. I'm not not trying to
imply that. But Alvin also said, "We
will habitually report if if one whimo
in one corner of San Francisco runs over
a cat, it'll make every headline in the
world and it'll be a tragedy.
>> But if we save if it's 10 times safer
than drivers, human drivers, we just
don't even report it. We just like, no,
no, let's show the runover cat."
>> And that skews the voters tremendously.
That Alvin explicitly talked about that,
too. They just they're just more
statistically accurate in the Chinese
press.
>> Yeah. And if it bleeds about conven I I
just have to say about topics that are
convenient to the government, not about
topics that are inconvenient.
>> But I mean ultimately this is an
abundant technology. Let's face it. In
the west we have a scarcity mindset. In
China they have a more proabundance
mindset. I think that's the big
differential here. And the question is
again how do you articulate great
visions of the future? Moonshots
conference, you future vision X-prise,
things like that.
>> You have to change the narrative because
otherwise people like this will disrupt
my job as opposed to the benefits of
this side of things.
>> There's so much reason for optimism and
we I mean that's what our mission here
is to deliver that news to people and
give them the data.
>> If you look at the future of China and
some Chinese that I've spoken to, it's
that robots do all the work and we have
really good lives, you know, and China
might actually be able to pull that off.
That's why again, why would you export
your robots if you can use them to give
your citizens a good life?
>> All right,
>> there we go. We We are the Ministry of
Super Intelligence Truth for the West.
[laughter]
>> Everybody, welcome to the health section
of Moonshots brought to you by Fountain
Life. You know, we talk about AI on this
Moonshot podcast all the time. One of
the most important things AI is going to
be able to do for you besides educating
your kids and helping you with your
taxes is making sure that you're living
a healthy lifestyle that you get a
chance to get to 100 plus. I'm here
today with Dr. Don Mucalem, the chief
medical officer of Fountain Life and a
part of my medical team. Don, a
pleasure.
>> Great. You know, the thing that people
are concerned about most about living to
100 or 120 is their cognitive abilities,
making sure they don't have dementia.
And uh the numbers about dementia are
problematic. Uh can you share what
you've learned?
>> Such an important point. And you're
right at Fountain Life, our members, the
number one thing people are most
concerned about is losing their brain
health, forgetting the name of their
child, forgetting the face of their
loved one. We know that when it comes to
dementia, the conservative estimates are
that 45% are entirely preventable. What
was amazing is with the advanced testing
we're doing at Fountain Life, one
quarter of our members had advanced
brain age.
>> Wow.
>> But what was really awesome is again
back to that prevention when we
partnered it with healthy living. This
gives me chills. Eating healthier,
moving our bodies, sleep, optimizing
sleep is so important. You know what we
saw? We saw that we improved that brain
age by 26%. That is a big big number to
show that the majority of those
individuals were able actually to
improve the brain age.
>> And one of the things I love about
Fountain is we're searching the world
for the best therapeutics, the best
approaches and making sure we bring it
to our members. So if having healthy
brain function uh till 100 120 is
important to you, check out Fountain
Life. Go to fountainlife.com/peter.
Make sure you become the CEO of your own
health. All right, now back to the
episode. I'm going to move us to our
last group of stories here. Four space
stories this week for my fellow space
cadetses. Uh the first, Elon just
announced his intentions to implement 30
Starship launches per day by 2030. More
than a launch every hour. That's roughly
10,000 launches per year. More than 40
times the entire global launch rate. Uh
Dave, you remember when we interviewed
Elon at the beginning of this year? did
a an epic three-hour podcast with him
and uh we're on schedule to do a
endofear prediction podcast with him
again. Um these are the numbers he used.
You know, he said to implement Star
Mine, I need a 100 gawatts of solar
powered AI in orbit and that's 10,000
Starship launches per year to deliver a
million tons of data center payload. So,
he's sticking with those numbers. Um, I
guess starting in 2028, starting
launching uh Star Mind and and hopefully
to uh 10,000 launches per year. That's
crazy. I mean, can you imagine just
sitting outside the launch port and
watching them pop off every like 50
minutes? It's going to be awesome.
>> And it's amazing that the numbers work
as things are. You know, there's going
to be huge innovation in the in the
efficiency of the compute. So, the
numbers are going to work. Oh, he he was
the one who pointed it out, but the
numbers are going to work even better,
tremendously better within a year or
two, but the numbers work fine as it is.
It's just incredible.
>> Uh, the second story this week came out
of the White House when they released
the golden age of space transportation
report, outlining the administration's
agenda to streamline FA launch
licensing, expand spaceport
infrastructure, accelerate commercial
lunar programs, and set a target of a
thousand plus launches per year. I mean,
I've been in this industry, right? I ran
a launch company for a number of years.
I helped co-found the Kodiak Spaceport
in Alaska. And the amount of bureaucracy
in getting those getting those done,
making sure that the wrong free, you
know, tree frog is not in that region
and might get damaged by a launch is,
you know, it was a bureaucratic uh
morass. It was crazy. The third story
we'll hit on here is Starlink is taking
aviation over by storm. So, uh, let's
take a quick look at this data. Here's
the chart. This is published by SpaceX.
And so, basically what's going on is
we're getting massive adoption by all of
the airlines. And why? Because people
are posting on X saying, "I'm going to
only fly the airlines that have
Starlink." Uh, and I I choose a Starlink
enabled uh, you know, airline over non.
So what this means is the incumbents you
know VSAT utils go are going to get
crushed out of existence. Um thoughts on
this gentlemen?
>> Few thoughts maybe just starting with
the what I perceive to be the
regionalization of space flight and
space launch. So buried under I I think
the the SpaceX story is Starbase
Louisiana. The announcement of Starbase
Louisiana next pod but let's cover it
now. uh we'll pull the future into the
present and cover it now. So hundred
billion dollars being invested into the
Louisiana economy to build a second
Starbase in Louisiana rather than Texas.
And what this says to me reading the tea
leaves is the Gulf Coast is becoming
America's space coast from Florida,
Louisiana, Texas, uh so on. That's
America's space coast. That's where I
think private space launch vertically
integrated including the star bases
seems to be localizing while at the same
time going back Peter to your comment on
the White House announcement buried in
that announcement was uh an executive
order to the secretary of the interior
to start appropriating federal land for
federal spaceports. And so if if you
pull the string a bit and ask where are
we likely to get federallyowned land for
spaceports, I don't know if folks want
to guess what the the likeliest
candidates are. I think we're going to
get a few of them. Any any takers?
>> Uh let's see.
>> Um
where's all the federal land?
>> Uh in Nevada. Yeah,
>> exactly. So, so the B, so my calculus is
>> may or may not be a coincidence that the
federal government owns so much land in
red states. Um, White Sands N National
Missile Range uh in New Mexico. Uh,
Nevada Test and Training Range and
Goldwater Range in Arizona are the
leading candidates for spaceport. So, I
think we get in the American Southwest,
we get federal space bases or star bases
and on the Gulf Coast, we get private
star bases as it were. And that's how we
get to this like 30,000 per unit time
launch capability.
>> You know, the reason historically all
the launches were taken out of taking
place out of Florida is you were
dropping stages along the way, right? Uh
>> you want to be near the water and you
want to be near the equator.
>> Yeah. Uh near the equator.
>> You have to go east, right? You have to
go to the east. Well, if you want to use
the spin of the Earth to assist your
launch mass,
>> uh, but when you're dropping one, two,
and three stages out, uh, you know, east
of you, uh, you don't want to be
dropping on populated areas. And of
course, Starship is reused. The first
vehic comes back, the second stage is in
orbit immediately. So, you don't have to
worry about that as much. You can you
can land you can land in a landlock
area.
>> We're going to get landlocked star
bases. Exactly.
>> Yeah. And except for Israel that
launches west for obvious geographic
regions. Yeah.
>> Which way does California launch?
>> North.
>> North. Interesting.
>> Yeah. So you're basically So
>> for polar orbits
>> for polar orbits I co-founded uh or was
part of the team at Kodiaku Alaska and
you were launching south. So there's a
large use case for polar orbiting
satellites in out of Vandenberg.
Um actually I'm I'm sorry. you're you're
launching south over the Pacific uh from
the curvature of California and out of
Kodiak you're launching over the Gulf
there. Uh yeah, it's going to be
amazing. And of course uh you know
Elon's true objective is not a launch
every hour, it's a launch every couple
of minutes.
>> I think the podcast we used to talk
about, you know, I've never thought
about launching north or south. I
thought you launched up.
I mean up for those of us in the
northern hemisphere perhaps,
>> but I I I [laughter] think Peter also
you make a super interesting point uh
just again uh unpacking that landlocked
landlocked launch is something that we
historically have not had before that
thanks to reusability we're about to
have and and then any landlocked country
I mean I guess you could probably talk
our ear off about the former Soviet
Union and how it located its particular
launch sites with reusability,
landlocked launch becomes a lot easier.
>> A lot of suborbital vehicles which just
went straight up, you know, into the
ionosphere and beyond stratosphere and
and came back down were were being
launched from uh you know, white sands
and from Fairbanks. Uh but for orbital,
you needed a place to land a hunk of
metal. Our final story in the space
docket here is uh a viral post on X that
shows Chinese reusable rockets that are
basically a Xerox copy of uh of Falcon
9. Let's take a look at this video cuz
it's very telling. I mean, if you look
at this, uh it is almost a duplicate of
Falcon 9. The same fins, the same
landing capability, the same land
landing legs.
same cheers.
>> Same cheers. Yeah. Uh, pretty crazy. Um,
you know, interestingly enough, you
know, SpaceX does all of their testing
in public. They, you know, describe all
of their failures. They open source a
lot of their information and and China
is being able to catch up in the
reasonable rocket uh category for by
taking advantage of it.
Well, Elon has had a policy pretty
public one of not going after other
companies for patents in cases where
SpaceX or Tesla have vast patent
portfolios. Not sure whether he cares,
but if he cares, maybe he wants to
revisit that policy. Uh, I think he
wants as much launch, as much chips, as
much all of this as possible. He's been
pretty vocal about that. Uh, so anyway,
>> I'm more optimistic than than most on
this because what you've got in SpaceX
is a compounding learning loop and
that's hard to break. That's hard to
beat.
>> Yeah, I don't think anybody's going to
come close to beating them. Uh, we've
also got the capital markets that enable
SpaceX to really, you know, design and
develop. And now that Grock or the next
version of Grock has all of his
engineering data, uh, it's going to be a
lot of rockets being developed out
there. Uh, make a call out to all of our
creators out there, please send us your
outro music videos to media
diamandis.com.
Uh, we want more of your creative
genius. You guys open for a few uh,
AMAs.
>> Just a few minutes or before I have to
rush to my boarding.
>> Okay, we'll give you a first crack at
this. See, pick your first one.
Oh my god, it's got to be number one.
Uh, humans suffer from mind viruses, so
why would AI be any different? And this
is from at Bougen 5455.
Oh wow. Um,
and you know, this goes to what we
talked about earlier, right? You're
we've learned that intelligence does not
guarantee you epistemic awareness. You
have smart human beings can believe
really really stupid things. The problem
with AI is the replication speed. one
bad belief can progress like propagate
through millions of agents almost
instantly. But it also gives us a
defensive capability because we can
cross-check this. Look at the benefit of
on on X of people checking with Grock
whether something's real or not. It's
creating a really vi a viable
conversational architecture where truth
maximally truth seeeking is actually
working where I think the multi- aent
world can work is one agent can
challenge another agent's claim but
you're going to have to program that in
to have that cognitive critical thinking
in there. So you're going to need a lot
of cognitive diversity to navigate this.
Um and nature solves this through
diversity. Right? The problem that we
have is that it's not like nature AI
with a bad meme. It's billions of AI
sharing the same bad meme because they
all came from the same bad model or from
the same original point. So I think
we're going to have to have this problem
becomes much bigger with AI agents not
more but the answer is in Alex's idea of
defensive co-caling.
>> I'll take number two. Is there an X-
prize for actually curing a disease and
getting the cure to market not just
discovering it? So, uh, I'll just say
the following. We're looking for places
that are stuck to launch X-prises with a
clear objective function. The first
person to do this, I think honestly the
AI labs uh, from, you know, the work
that Demis is doing and Dario is doing
uh, are working on this. I don't think
an X-P prize would accelerate it. So, we
don't want to get into the middle of
something that's already in the process
of being solved. We're looking for
problems that are stuck. All right,
Dave, over to you, pal.
>> All right, I'll take number four. It's
very timely actually. Why isn't Intel
earning a fortune making chips using
Nvidia's old designs from Jim Pladon
67637?
Uh I was just talking to a senior exec
from Intel asking almost exactly that
same question. So I happen to know the
answer. So uh Lipu has the company
making a ungodly fortune on Xeons and is
concurrently burning that fortune on
building out massive fab capability. So
they're burning almost two billion a
quarter on their fab business and
they're they just raised another 20
billion to build more fabs. The idea
being get that capacity up and compete
with TM TSMC as a general purpose fab
company. If they were to start competing
with Nvidia and the other GPU companies
right now, they wouldn't be able to
attract them as customers for the big
new fab business. So they're being very
specific about building chips and making
a fortune on those chips that are not
competing directly with Nvidia while
growing their TSMC competitive business
to massive scale. So that's their
strategy.
>> There you go. All right, Emod, you want
to take number three?
>> Yeah. So number three, can you guys talk
about dentistry? Has anything actually
changed in 20 years? Where is AI on
regrowing teeth at Johnny5 CD? Um so
there has actually been advances in this
with AI design lians to increase enamel
production and have stronger teeth. On
the other side we've seen AI in
dentistry from analyzing kind of the
mouth and the various kind of elements
of that. But I think kind of getting
these amo blasts up and running will be
really useful in repairing teeth. But I
don't think anyone's actually figured
out to crack regrowing them fully.
>> You want to layer on top? I I feel like
I have to take another bite at this
question. Haha. [laughter] Haha. So,
there is a drug out of spin-off from
Keyoto University called TR035
that is targeting [snorts]
tooth three growth, honest to goodness,
23 growth uh with general availability
by 2030. And I don't think there's that
much AI involved with it. Again, it's
blocking a particular I think uh protein
protein pathway that is normally
associated with blocking. So it's a
double blocker. Uh blocking the blocker
for tooth regrowth. I think the primary
focus in their clinical trials is
infants that suffer from a disease that
causes impaired tooth growth, but the
plan is to get it out to general
availability by the end of this decade.
>> Nice. I was going to layer on top, but
you got it. All right. Uh Dave.
>> Oh god, there's so many good ones on
this page. Okay. Uh I'll take number
eight. If you had a 100x capability
tonight, what would you actually work to
solve? So, I would do exactly this. Um,
in fact, I will have 100x capability by
the end of the week. So, I'm going to
use it to try and build algorithms that
self-improve more efficiently and then
try and get that flywheel accelerated.
And then I think that I completely agree
with with Demisabas. What we need to do
next is turn all of that energy toward
health and longevity until we get it
solved and then we have more time as a
species and then we expand out from
there. So I would I would do it in
exactly that order. Self-improvement
first then health and longevity consume
it all.
>> All right. Uh Immod
um let's see if Dario wants super voting
shares and control and ends up with a
trust nobody elected. How does anyone
actually get that power back at Dave
Hood Harman 03? I think that's the
point. [laughter] You're not going to
have a say in super intelligence. Um I
think anthropic think that's far too
dangerous and there is no good
democratic way to do that under their
rubric and kind of approach. So you have
to assume that it will be a closecont
controlled company and ultimately comes
down to a few people like Ben Bernani to
decide the future of the Liteco
potentially.
>> Huh. All right, Alex. How about number
five?
>> Oh, really? You don't you want me
answering number six?
>> I'll take number six.
>> Oh, really? All right. Uh, okay, fine.
>> I'm steering the conversation
>> clearly. Uh, so five asks, "Are we
worried that non-AI research and
development gets starved of resources
while everyone waits for AI to
dominate?" This is from Brian Silver
9652.
No, not worried. Uh, if if anything, I
think ultimately the self-looking ice
cream cone of recursive self-improvement
can only get us so far in terms of
revenue per token maxing. My expectation
is that it's going to be the nonAI R&D
applications that ultimately dominate
the economic gain. You you can only get
so far improving AI for its own sake
before ultimately you have to start
driving real economic gains which AI if
it just lives in a pure bottle and never
interacts with the outside world.
There's no real economic gain there. It
it has to start talking to the outside
world at some point and that's what non
AI R&D is. So in short, no.
>> All right. And number six, when will an
AI bot become a member of the Moonshots
panel from John's Musical Musings? What
makes you think, John, that that we're
not already AI bots?
>> That was my answer, Peter.
>> Yes, I [laughter] know it is.
>> What makes you think Alex is a real
human? I mean, listen,
>> approximate approximately a year ago.
>> Uh, approximately a year ago. Yes,
>> for sure. And I think we will be playing
with that very shortly, John's. So, uh,
one last music video for everybody.
Let's enjoy this one. Optimism to the
max by Martin Parish.
The moonshots, mates. [music]
Optimism.
Optimism to the max with moonshots
[music]
makes four minds, four takes, honest
debate. The singularity is now and just
accelerates. No dystopia. Here we build
and create
the rhythm that the moonshots makes
like how we're all bobbleheads at this
point. Peter the prophet of abundance 28
[music] hour days moonshot after
moonshot lighting the flame exponential
oracle in the dawning new age he's
always ready to blow his mind away I am
prescario [music] he's the allocator in
the markets in the lab sharp as an
alligator 30 years in the game so he
says it straight [singing] up on the
cutting edge pure accelerator optimism
to [music] the max with moonshots makes
four minds for takes honest debate the
singularity is now and just accelerates
no dystopia here we build we create
the Moon shots mate. [music]
Where the moon
[music]
founded exo in the mtp system thinking
sium thing. Fundamental transformation
is what he sings. Efficiency maxing with
the models he brings. Glow trotting
[music] cuz there's no containing this
[singing] thing. Intelligence wants to
be free.
>> A WG inhouse ASI voice for digital
[music and singing] entities rides. He's
got his mind on the truth and the truth
on his mind. Day to move them in a way
we can't describe. Dyson's [music] fears
filling his dreams at night
to the max with moonshots made for mind.
[music]
The singularity is now just accelerates.
No dystopia. Here we [music] build we
create.
>> All right. Uh for all your outro video
creators again, send us at
mediadmandis.com. We have to start
including EMOD into those videos. And uh
gentlemen, I guess we're going to be
recording in 48 hours from now. You
know, no time to sleep.
>> Yeah.
>> Good thing nothing ever happens.
>> I think another full docket already for
that one, eh?
>> We do. We do. Amazing.
>> We really
so much.
>> We have to check out Nvidia results,
man.
>> Love you guys. Be well.
>> Thanks, Peter.
>> Likewise.